He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our
More time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host
this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, Christ is risen.
He truly is risen.
Welcome, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
We are recording life,
but we're not going to be taking any phone calls tonight.
That said, if you leave a question on our Facebook
or our ancient faith YouTube streams and we spot it,
it is possible.
that we might take and respond.
So tonight our topic is profits.
What is prophecy?
Who is a profit?
Do profits predict the future?
Does prophecy still happen in our times?
What's the difference between a profit and a possible?
How can we recognize a true profit or prophecy?
What about people who claim to have prophecies even now?
So it's been a while since we did this,
few episodes maybe,
but we always love going back to the ancient near East.
and it turns out that there is
a larger context for prophecy than just what we see in the Bible.
So where are we starting tonight, Father Stephen?
Well, I'm starting with a disclaimer.
Okay.
Because I know ancient faith is a big tent, right?
We have lots of different podcasts, lots of different voices, lots of different opinions.
But that guy who's podcast, you were playing right before we went on the air.
Oh yes, that guy.
I do not want to be associated with him in any way.
So I disavow that person and everything he is.
That's good.
Just for the record.
Well thanks for that.
That's taking care of.
Right, we can now move on.
Right, right.
So we're starting, yeah, we're starting in the ancient air east.
Right.
That's a broad swap.
Sort of the earliest written material we're going to be starting with is going to come from the 18th century.
BC. So 1700 BC. So for us, relatively recently. Yeah. Now, this is, I say that, that is not
sort of when the idea of a profit or prophecy sort of begins, right? This is just sort of the
earliest written sources we have that we found so far that we have to talk about tonight. But the time
I'm gonna get there.
the idea of profits and prophecy are already established. Right? There are already
multiple terms in different Semitic languages for profits and prophecy. The idea
of a profit is a known quantity. Right? So, someone is identified as a profit. People know
So what that means, already.
So this is something that goes back.
Centuries and centuries and centuries before even the 18th century BC, but we have to start where we have sort of data
and records, right exactly
In terms of getting getting specific, but before we get specific
We'll get a little general right because we have to first kind of talk about what prophecy was
Mm-hmm in a broad sense. So a lot of times
today, when people talk about profits.
or call someone a profit, it's about, as you kind of mentioned in your intro there,
it's about predicting the future. Right, so people want to find a profit,
you can tell the future if they're in the stock market, they want to find a profit, you can
and profit-style profits.
But that's not really what it's about.
Yeah, is that really what it's...
about. So prophecy as such is sort of a subspecies of divination. Right.
Devining and people may not have noticed before that divination involves the word divine.
Right, yeah, it's about talking to gods or some kind of spirit.
to or trying to get some kind of knowledge that you could not otherwise know by divine assistance
in some way.
Right.
So there's a divine realm.
There is a divine perspective, which is greater than the perspective of humans.
Right.
There is a wisdom that divine being fabric understated.
or knowledge that they have a perspective of that, that human beings are otherwise privy
to. And so, divination as a broad category consists of various ways in which humans have
or have tried to sort of access that wisdom or knowledge, right? Either with the spirits
of cells or through signs left by the spirits or some means by which spirits were thought
to communicate. Now that includes, as we've talked about many times and we talked about
this, or we talked about apocalyptic, I know. This includes the fact that divine beings have
a different relationship with time than humans do.
Yeah, right. So they might know things that it seemed like they're from the future,
or whatever.
Right, right, or from the distant past.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, and we see this like for example in Isaiah when Yahweh the God of Israel is talking
about the gods of the nations and comparing himself to them.
He says, you know, who will tell you about the things in the past?
Right?
How the earth was formed?
All these things.
Who will tell you about those things in the future?
So that is applying that, yeah, we're the God of Israel.
the one who truly has this total and complete perspective.
Yeah.
Unlike the fallen spirits who are the gods, right?
Who may have a greater knowledge or sense
of these things than humans, but don't really
have the knowledge and wisdom that the true God possesses.
Yeah, they're much bigger and smarter than us,
but they're not omniscient, they're not omnipotent,
they're not omnipresent.
They can't know everything.
So, within divination, you have a whole bunch of things.
And so, a lot of these things in the ancient Near East and the ancient Near World in general
are related to employing some kind of technique or reading signs.
So, probably the most obvious and well-known one of those today would be astrology.
Yeah, looking at the stars and figuring out what's going on there.
Right.
stars of the planets are seen to be sort of divine beings and so there could be some communication
for the divine realm there.
There could be red but again there's a technique there right you have star charts right
and you said there plot the movements of the constellations of the planets right and
so it's a person who's going to participate in that is going to be a specialist right
he's going to be somebody who has devoted this time and study to it.
Well, no.
one would be a horoscopes, plural horoscisese.
It's about guts.
Yeah, who we've also talked about before, they got guts.
Who would read the entrails of sacrificial animals, recite?
And there's a whole, like, subspecies, well not subspecies of that, but there's a whole
variant in this which is about watching animal movements, right? Like...
My favorite is Mirmo Mancy, which is reading the signs by watching ants.
But also, a Luromancy, which is about watching cats.
I can't remember the term for birds.
I don't know.
Birds was actually more common than either of the other animals.
Yes, yes, right.
For example.
I know, I know.
But I love the idea that people, I mean, it's a real thing.
People actually would watch ants to try to read the sides.
Right.
Because built into the world, there are spirits connected to all of these things.
So those spirits could potentially communicate through them.
But again, it's all technique.
So your heart respects, we have a lot of them, because they're fired clay, so they basically
last forever.
Livers and kidneys, like models with little notations on them of what to look for in different places.
So this is again your...
specialists, right? And this is what most pagan priests were, frankly, in the ancient world.
Yeah. Most pagan priests, they were not like preaching servants and giving counseling. Right? They
running various council meetings doing Stuart's programs to the big thermometer. Yeah, no.
They were specialists, right?
So like if you go to the early
the old kingdom of Egypt, for example, and even the middle kingdom.
Like most of the priests were basically people who could read and write.
Yeah, and including that is reading signs, omens, you know.
Right, right.
So if you could read and write, you were a priest, right, and you're in time to keep all the sacred texts,
which texts contained the methods for reading all of these things.
So you're sort of preserving this knowledge, right?
And...
The horoscopes of the priests, you knew how to read the signs of entree.
They knew these particular things.
We see this in the Bible too, like when people are called into interpret dreams by like
Nebuchadnezzar.
Yeah, right.
Right.
There were priests who that was their job, that was what they had studied and mastered,
right?
Long time before Freud, right?
They figured out the interpretation of dreams.
And so this is, it's a specialist.
knowledge thing right and plays into a lot of the things we've talked about like
with with the watchers of the of Kahlu in this knowledge that gets revealed yeah right then then
um so um
yeah so prophecy is also a sub-species of divination but it's different than those other ones we've
been talking about because unlike those prophecy was not primarily there are there's exceptions
and say everything.
Right, but for the most part prophecy did not involve that kind of technique
Right, it was not about reading signs
It was about a
Direct more direct encounter and direct relationship between the person who's considered a prophet and
The deity yeah, right who for whom they are a prophet and there is a relationship there where somebody's a prophet of
of
this god or this small group of gods right they were just a prophet in general and then different
you know gods came and whispered in their ears right there was a hit ongoing sort of direct
relationship between them and some spiritual being yeah and that that took a couple of forms
in the sense that on one hand you have prophets the way we tend to think about them like in the old
Testament.
where it's a question of contact and interaction between the two.
Then you also have what are usually called oracles
or some version of that, right?
Where the spirit actually like possesses the person
and like literally speaks through them, right?
Right.
So more like the council of the gods in moonlight
Then that.
then you're typical people. I haven't watched it. I know I haven't watched it. It's on my list. I don't know.
Yeah. Yeah.
But so those are sort of self-reliant, but in both of those cases, it's direct.
There's not sort of an intermediary of birds or answer stars or guts.
right through which some kind of messages convey it's a direct sort of
relationship and
Sort of the phenomenon of prophecy from what we could tell again. We go by the evidence we have
Seems to have primarily been a phenomenon in some minic area
So it's it's less pronounced you get more of other forms of divination
In Egypt for example. Yeah, there are some sort of profit things that you would call prophecy as a phenomenon in Egypt
So that totally...
absent, but it's much less prominent than other types of divination.
Egypt, we don't have really record of a lot of prophecy among the hit types, for example,
where it had no European people.
But even among Semitic people in the Near East, it's kind of a scattered thing.
And again, we're going based on evidence, right?
So maybe less scattered than we think, right?
range don't have the the
and stuff, but from what we can tell, right, there are certain periods and certain places
where this phenomenon comes to a great prominence, and then others where we don't find and read
a lot about it.
And that includes, right, it's not purely fragmentary evidence because there are places and periods
where we have a lot of written records and don't see much about prophecy.
Yeah.
Right, so it's not purely the fragmentary.
evidence, but we always have to have that as a proviso, right? There could be a big textual
fine tomorrow that could change that, right? Hypothetically. So, now that we've done that
general kind of thing, we want to look at more in particular a couple of those places where
sort of prophetic activity in the ancient Near East sort of starts to flourish. And the first one of
of these.
These are written records that come from before any part of the Bible was written down.
Right. Because this is we're talking now 18th century BC.
Is that before Abraham even?
Well, Abraham didn't write anything.
Yeah, right. But I mean, I don't know if you've been hanging out with Mormons.
No.
You actually did not.
Little, little known fact about me actually I've been to more
Mormon historical sites than most Mormons, which whenever I meet a Mormon and tell them that they're like,
you are so blessed. I'm like, well, I'm interested in religious history, but that's so great. Do you feel,
and I know I don't, but thank you. So anyway, I was physically ejected from the temple in Salt Lake City,
but that's a story for another time. Yeah, it is. How many holy sites have you been ejected from?
Probably less blastin'
That's great for the eyes of most of our LBS friends.
Wow.
You have to use that one for a fundraiser.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so this is after Abraham lived.
After Abraham lived.
But I'm still bored by arguments about the date of Moses,
but even on the earliest possible date, or I should say,
The earliest suggests.
and puts them in the 16th century BC, this is older, right, by a couple centuries, right.
So no text that's currently in the Bible had been written down, doesn't mean the stories didn't exist,
right, because it means things didn't happen, but nothing had been written down at the time of
the writings we're about to talk about. And so these are usually called the Mari documents or
the Murray letters because they're found in a city called
Yeah, M-A-R-I, right?
Yeah.
Right.
And so, yeah, super creative name for them.
It's better than the usual way the documents get named,
where do you get like A36, or they get a letter in a number.
Yeah.
Gothic P46.
Yeah, right.
So, except if I ever let me bow today, if I am...
find a trope of basic documents like this.
The letter before the numbers will be in Comic Sans.
I'm doing it.
Wow.
So the cruel joke for the ages.
Yeah.
So the, the, the Mari documents, right,
or the Mari letters are from the city of Mari,
which was in sort of the central Euphrates region,
so part of Akad.
Yeah.
And, you know, folks, you can look this up.
actually look up where
this is a Wikipedia, Mari, comma, Syria, M-A-R-I, comma, Syria, and you'll get
Cuneiform right there in the top. Hey.
And yes, Cuneiform, these are clay tablets. That's why they survive.
And so there's a massive trove of these. And a lot of them are
communications for people who identify themselves as prophets.
And they're contained in here.
things referring to both male and female prophets of different gods. But this is also important because
this is not just an example of prophecy, like the phenomenon of prophecy that we see in the scriptures,
but these are also then writing prophets, right? Prophets who write things down or whose prophecies are
written out. Yeah, so they become sacred texts maybe, maybe...
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah, they write their writing.
So that then puts it in a genre that's similar to big chunks of the Old Testament.
Yeah, right.
So this idea that the prophecies of a prophet would be written down or that a prophet himself
might send it in the form of a letter, right?
It's not sort of a new phenomenon in the Old Testament.
This is something that's already been around.
Great in the ancient
in the past year. And I copied over, complete with weird
lacunai notations. And before I edited it, weird Greek letters
inserted in places and things. Despite just one of these
it's semi-random. But this is, this is like a typical one.
Yeah. And we should say that you get a flavor of what
it sounds like. Even though there were random Greek letters,
this was not in Greek. It was not written with Greek letters.
It was a cut and paste thing.
Right, yeah, because I had to get it out of this.
So this is my flight. I got it out of this book published by SBL,
where they had the
transliterated accadian in one column.
And then the English translation in the other column.
And I had to try to pull the text out of the English column.
And I ended up with all kinds of weird and critical marks and stuff.
I feel your pain.
Yeah, yes, yes.
It was a tragedy.
if you want to support
me in my plate you can paypal me and help us wage my difficult work. I will consider that.
So I'm going to read this and like you said this is just like a sort of a typical one of these
Cuneiform tablets from the Maari letters. Moreover a prophet of Adad, Lord of Aleppo, came with Abu
Dalim and spoke to him as follows. Right to your Lord the following. Am I not Adad, Lord of Aleppo,
who raised you in my lap and restored you to and you
ancestral throne, I do not demand anything from you. When a wronged man or woman cries out to you,
be there and judge their case. This only I have demanded from you. If you do what I have written to
you and heed my word, I will give you the land from the rising of the sun to its setting, your land
greatly increased. This is what the prophet of A.D. Lord of Aleppo said in the presence of Abu Dallim,
My Lord should know this.
Not that exciting, Riley.
No, but this is, again, it's just sort of t-
Yeah, right. Yeah, and so Abu Dallim is some kind of scribe, right to whom the prophet comes
as a say write this down to the king, right?
And he's
bringing this word from ad ad the god of Aleppo.
So
Yeah, I'm gonna do it. I would pause here and talk a little trash on herman and gong call.
I don't even know what our German scholar friend. Oh, okay. So
for 150 years probably.
I think he's well not that long but you know not long enough probably.
So you may have noticed when you're hearing that right that sounds a lot like a lot of
prophecies in the Bible.
Yeah it's very similar to a lot of what you get from the Bible.
Right in the format and everything right.
So, Gunko was a big guy and profanic.
form criticism.
Okay.
And so what form criticism does is you get sort of all the examples of a genre you can.
Right.
And then you categorize them.
Right. So, Gunko did lie. Well, this is an oracle of judgment against a person.
This is an oracle of judgment against a king. This is an oracle of judgment against a nation.
This is an Oracle Deliverance for a Nation.
This is right, categorizes them all, right?
And sort of tries to find patterns in the genre.
Yeah.
And then, because this is like what German scholars do,
they just taxonomize and catalog everything, right?
And so he's including the Old Testament stuff in this
and then stuff like the Murray documents,
all these kinds of things.
So some of the other stuff we're going to talk about in a minute.
There was an all in there.
and then
he says, right, well, okay, so any time a prophecy in the Bible follows the
format. Now these are templates that he's created based on his taxonomy, right?
So every time it follows the template, it's unimportant and not interesting.
Right? It's the only important part of any biblical prophecy is if you could
to fight a place where it breaks from the template.
Right? And so that you take wherever it breaks from the template. Now mind you this is a template that he made up.
Yeah, right.
Based on the limited examples we have that have survived to his day.
So that if he finds a place that breaks the template, then you read everything into that word or phrase.
Right. That you didn't find in all the other similar ones.
Yeah, and that.
That becomes what the whole thing is about.
So this has been another episode of why most biblical scholarship is kind of goofy.
By the way, I looked at it.
Father Steven D.
And we should that should have its own theme.
Chris Hoyle you know what to do.
Yeah, no, I looked it up and he died in 1932.
So he's been gone for 90 years.
I was not that long.
Yeah, not 150.
but at nine years. Yeah, yeah, early 20th century German friend. Yeah, yeah, so
but the reason why I wanted not just because I like picking on Germans, I mean,
you know, they spent the 20th century picking on the rest of us, so it's very game. But, wow,
Wow.
It's not just because I like picking up Germans.
It's that, right?
This is...
This is an example of how to do what we try to do on the show, how we try to use this
kind of data, like the Mari letters, or things from the ancient Near East, or Second Temple
Jewish literature.
How to use that really badly.
And really unhelpfully.
It's very scholarly and very academic.
This sort of categorized and dex-automized everything.
I don't begrudge him
that, publish your journal article.
Sure, right.
You do you.
But it's, but like, would the people who use this
as part of their live culture and religion
have understood it that way?
Right, right.
And for a chunk of the 20th century,
Google's stuff was being taught in like seminaries.
Yeah.
And grad schools, as how to interpret
prophetic texts of the Old Testament.
Right?
And it just kind of makes a mess of it, right?
It just kind of makes a mess of it.
So rather than seeking to learn what we can learn
about the background of the ancient Near East
and how prophecy function like we're trying to do tonight,
how did prophecy function in the ancient Near East?
Okay, now that we've talked about that a little now,
let's look at the biblical text and see if that
enlightens us on anything that's sort of in the background
here, right?
Of these prophets and prophetic books.
Yeah.
trying to play out and reduce the biblical tax to, right, there's nothing
privileging the book of Amos for Gunkal over one of the Mari letters.
It's the same thing, right, and it's only even interesting, again, if there's
something quote-unquote weird in it, based on his established normal.
Right, and so when you attack things in that way, you really aren't attacking them.
Right? You rather than sort of deepening the meaning and understanding of the biblical
tax, you just kind of make it uninteresting and irrelevant. Right? Right. So anyway, now
I'm done with with Gunnkel. That's what he said. Right. But yeah. Yeah. But I think it's
important that once in a while we point to these things because every once in a while, there's
someone on the internet who doesn't like this show.
Out there they are.
to believe I know. Right. Right. But. And one of the things is one of the sort of need your
criticisms we get is that they're taking all this biblical scholarship and that wrecks
the Bible. Right. And it's not that that's totally like a can. Right. Right. There's
scholarship and there's scholarship. There are modes of doing it. Yes. Right. That sort
relative eyes and negate the force of the text of Scripture and stuff right.
there certainly are approaches to do that.
But the fact that we talk about the sanctionary system,
there are also ways to read this stuff
and understand this stuff that actually helps
to deepen the understanding of the biblical text, right?
And you can differentiate those at the level of method.
Okay, so I know banging on beating Grunkel's dead horse.
Yes, his name is either dead or I don't know.
90-year-old, the horse, yeah.
So, but what that text of that Murray letter that you read also shows us is that even in
Murray, this prophet sort of shows up and says this to the king, and that means this prophet,
his sort of authority and his voice is derived directly from the deity also, meaning he stands
apart from the king.
He's able to come and tell the king something.
Yeah, he's not.
part of the King's administration.
He's not appointed to that position by the King.
You know, it's not, he's not part of the establishment.
I think is one of the big things
to take away from this right here.
Yeah.
So the King is himself a priest.
And we're talking about divine kingship.
Yeah, divine kingship at this point in history.
Right.
So one of the gods.
And so his priests are, as we were just
saying mostly what we would call the miners of various kinds.
So you have that establishment and then you have a prophet who drives their ability to
speak directly from this God who is at least the king's equal because they think the king's
divine.
But who can then come and challenge the king and tell the king what to do or correct the
king?
remind the king of his duty to establish justice.
which most people could not get away with doing,
shall we say, if they wanted to live?
Right.
So the profit has this kind of outsider role to the establishment,
right here in the ancient areas.
Another place where we see sort of a flowering of prophetic activity
is actually in and around Nineveh.
the seventh century BC. Yeah, good old. They see where we're going with this.
So, Minneveld this time is the capital of the Assyrian Empire. Yep.
The Assyrians made those 20th century Germans. I was joking darkly about earlier.
Look like choir boys.
They were
Possibly, again, based on records.
Possibly the most group...
Imperial receiving the history of the world.
Yeah, is this where we recommend everyone listen to the fall of civilizations podcast
again?
About a Syria.
Yeah, they did an episode on a Syria, which I can't remember how long it was.
You know, like people think that this podcast as long as that episode, that show is routinely
four hours.
Yeah.
I also recommend their YouTube channel too.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Got some nice visuals.
They've taken the audio podcast and they just sort of put really high quality, sometimes
like 4k.
Let me be-
visuals of actual like archaeological sites and stuff to give you an idea of the places that are being talked about.
But yeah, I mean, it's been a while since I listened to the Assyria episode, but yes, I mean, you
it is, they are some mean, mean people. I think it was a really nasty empire. And I mean, and these are the people that carry off the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
Right. Yeah. Right. Which ceases to exist. Right.
So yeah, they're incredibly brutal, but also there is this flowering, a seventh century,
of prophecy that we have from written sources again, right?
They tell us they have this tradition of prophets, which again, this is standing apart from the Assyrian king,
who's seen as a divine king, his priesthood, right, of dividers and that kind of thing, right?
Who are doing their thing?
to try and get the signs of God's.
But also just it was a phenomenon
that a prophet could arrive,
bringing a message from one of the gods
and deliver to the king or deliver it to the civilization.
And this is in the background of course, then,
and helps us understand what's going on in the book of Jonah.
Yeah, when he just sort of shows up out of the blue
and says, you know, how is it?
In 40 days, whatever, Nineveh will be overthrown,
or is it
three days I can't remember off the top of my head now. And they are able to receive that.
And they're not like, who's this wacky Hebrew? You know, why should we listen to this guy? It's
because like, wait, this guy fits into, he looks, he sounds, he smells like a prophet. Wow,
what he's saying stuff that's really scary. So maybe we should go ahead and listen to him.
So they're able to receive, they maybe his God isn't there, God. But you don't want to get a God
even if he's not your God.
kind of thing. Yeah, yeah. You know, and this is important for a couple of reasons. One,
I think a lot of people's picture of Jonah is sort of like he shows up in Nineveh and
you know, he's carrying around a sign saying the end is near like, you know, the crazy guy
outside Comic Con, you know. Right. But this is not he fits into for them. Right. This is a
phenomenon that they know about, right? And this also affects
You know, not just start 19th century German friends, but lots of our scholarly friends who
Will say well of course Jonas makes it all and couldn't have happened
Right there's no record of native or repenting or converting to the worship of Yahweh, right?
But that that's not what the text is talking about
Right the text is talking about them repenting
right because a prophet showed up and told them that there was a God who was very
angry at them.
done certain things.
So they perform rituals of repentance.
This explains why Jonah would have thought that was the likely result.
Remember the book of Jonah?
Jonah says after the fact that one of the reasons that he didn't want to go, to Dinova was
that he knew they did not repenting and God wouldn't nuke him.
After, you know, because Jonah remember goes and proclaims this to Dinova and then goes
and sort of set up as folded.
on a nearby hill to watch the fireworks.
Right.
And then it doesn't happen and he's all ticked off.
He's like, I knew this was going to happen.
So, right?
So why would he have suspected that?
This is the most brutal regime in the world.
Why would he have thought that if he walked into the capital city
of the most brutal regime in the world at the time
that they would have listened to what he said
about a god destroying the city and repentant?
Well, because the Ninevites had, right?
Right, this was a cultural idea.
Yeah, it's a thing.
Yeah, they understood, right?
So yeah, so this is a, those are just two examples,
but this is a known phenomenon.
So now we're going to talk a little bit about,
this isn't really Father Andrew's etymology
is here because it's going to be mostly
a cady and a neocere.
Yeah, Father Stevens at a biology corner.
What you step out of Indo-European, I'm pretty lost.
So some of these are very hard to pronounce, at least for me with my white boy town.
So we'll see how we do.
But so in a Canadian, right, a Canadian record, the most common title for a profit is Moufou
a male prophet.
and muhutu, muhutu, it's too sold for a female prophet. That too ending is, it's feminine.
In Neoesirian, it's makhu and makhu-tu. Right? So you can tell the difference, the consonants are the same. Right?
The difference is the vocalization, the vowels, you can say. Right? Because that's how civic languages work.
basically.
So those are the two main words.
Those are derived from the verb, the Akkadian verb, Mahu, which means to go insane basically
or to enter into a frenzy.
Yeah, kind of a crazy trance, altered consciousness, sort of a thing.
other grounds. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, what's interesting.
So I looked this up because I remembered a similar etymology.
So now I'll bring it over to the Indo-European world now.
So Odin, whose name really is actually properly Othin,
no one in any of the Norse periods from then
till now would have said Othin.
It was Othin.
So he, but Odin is the way we say it, generally in English.
His name means like the infuriated one.
And he is this God associated with wisdom and prophecy and visions.
You know, like that's what the whole single eye thing is kind of about, right, that he sees things.
And I'll, you know, I'll just finish out my little side break about Norse mythology by mentioning,
and I just learned this recently actually.
So I'm not, I can't, I'm not an expert in these things, but I'm, I'm learning them.
So apparently, cultic helmets related to odenic
religion have been found that have a mask included and in the helmet and on the one side,
if I remember correctly, the eye is sort of blocked or just nothing special about it
or whatever, but then on the other side, one eye has gems embedded around it in the helmet.
And the idea is that when you are entering into this, you know, I don't know if it's a
sacrificial space or whatever, but some kind of
space that would be dark, that would be only lit by
fire light. That what would happen then is the gem-studded eye on the
cultic helmet would sort of light up because of the light.
So the person wearing this helmet is kind of embodying Odin
and their one eye, the eye of wisdom, lights up, right?
The eye of seeing and prophecy and that kind of stuff.
So it is interesting that even though like, that's a very long distance
It's a very long distance from...
from the ancient near East, but this idea of frenzy
and prophecy kind of going together is totally a thing.
I mean, I don't know if this is the case
in Native North American and South American religions,
but I wouldn't be surprised if that same association
were not there as well.
Well, you even see it,
and this will be a non-controversial part of our show.
Hey, you even see it in the very early accounts
of Muhammad.
All right.
When he first received his visions, he's sort of in the state of terror and panic
Yeah, and even seems to be about to like throw himself up a cliff
So I mean that ancient ancient exceptions sticks around in the Middle East
6th and 7th century AD
Yeah, yeah, right
so
that kind of
And this is describing
sort of the state that's brought about by this sort of direct contact with the spiritual
being, right, that provokes this response. And so as we said before, there's sort of two
categories then of prophets in the sense that there are some of them who are sort of visionary
prophets with that external relationship, right, with the spirit, right, who usually describe
that interaction.
as seeing, as sort of encountering.
And that's usually in visual terms.
I would, well, we'll talk more about visions later on.
Yeah, I won't get into all that.
OK, we'll get to that later.
I'm about to digress about Aristotle a bunch of you, too.
And the other is...
that oracular, that internal, right, that possession, right, idea, right.
So those are the most common words for prophecy in this context.
There are a couple of others in a KDN, sometimes prophets are called Opilum, which means
answerer because it's from the verb Apollo, Apollo, that means to answer.
Right, so the idea is this.
This seems to convey a function more like, say, the Oracle at Delphi.
Someone comes to this person and asks them questions, inquires, in order to inquire of
the gods, rather than them showing up with a proclamation from the gods.
And now we're going to get weirder because with the assyriancent particular, there
There was a particular group called the Asin.
Okay, so what does that word mean?
That word means man-woman.
Well, there we are.
So these were people in a Syria who were men, but then the encounter they have with the
spiritual realm.
causes them in some way or another to sort of no longer be met.
So there is this sort of weird, liminal space between sexes and genders.
Yeah, and yeah, well, you know, to bring it back over to Odin, right?
So he was known to practice. Now this is from like, this is like from the real actual source texts that we have of Norse mythology,
I should say by the way
All are written down by Christians.
So we don't know that this is exactly Norse pagan religion.
We don't know, but this is what we've got.
So anyways, Odin practice this kind of divination called saithir.
S-E-I-E-E-V.
I don't know how you would call that letter in Norse,
but in Old English it's an E-V-R- saithir.
And it's considered to be disreputable kind of divination
because it in North society.
mostly associated with women. And in order for men to practice it, they have to cross
stress. So there is this again, like this sort of androgyny or, you know, liminal thing going
on in terms of prophecy, at least some particular kinds of prophecy that exists all the way
over there. And the reason why it's considered disruptible in Norse culture is that cross-dressing
was a big no-no. You know, like it was a dark, weird thing, you know, that you do. Very
different image.
of Odin then you get from the Marvel Cinematic Universe.
Yeah, although, hey, you never know what Anthony Hopkins might be upward in the next few
days.
That is true.
Yeah, and you see this kind of thing, lots of other places.
One place that gets sort of brushed up against in the New Testament is there was a cult center
to Kyberley
offer pronounced cybalm, or cybole, or cybole, or all kinds of different ways of things.
In Galatia, the region of Galatia. And those priests would, at a certain point in their
initiation, enter into this level of ecstasy at which they would amasculate themselves,
Yeah, he's physically.
And so then after that they too occupied this space and the Romans also found the whole
idea repulsive, which is saying something because the Romans were into some weird stuff, man.
Right.
But even the Romans think you're weird.
Yeah.
Even they had their limits.
They're like, man, this is just too weird for us.
So they would confine the priest of Cavalier to their temples.
wouldn't let them leave because they don't want to see them
except for one day a year where they can come out and beg
from people
of one of their feet. But so this isn't just a weird a Syrian thing right there are versions of this
right right and this is part of that frenzy that it's had this idea that
having this encounter with these spiritual forces sort of breaks people
But be careful.
Yeah.
They're touched, right?
I mean, that's what that word means.
Yeah, they're touched.
Ted.
In these pagan contexts, we're talking about like a Syria and in Kavalein and some of
these others, these pagan contexts.
You notice that it's like, it's always a destructive way.
Yeah.
Right.
It's not that they're made somehow like wiser and more virtuous by the experience that
they're made.
like crazy, right? Or they do physical harm to themselves, right? Or their roots from society
by no longer being able to function, if they wanted to, right? It's sort of a normal societal
cultural way. Yeah. Yeah. So there's one.
One more term before we leave our ancient Near Eastern terms.
And that's a neo-Syrian term, which is regamo is the verb that means to shout.
And so certain prophets are called either rangimu, if they're male or rangimu, see that
too feminine ending again. If they're female.
And that literally means like, shouners or yellowers.
But this is the kind of idea between the Greek word
that becomes a port in the scripture
more on this later of Karegma, the idea of a message
that's proclaimed.
So these would be, if the answers are more like the Orgledel
if I could go and consult with, this would be designated
this profit is more the tie who shows up yelling at you.
The end is near or whatever.
Right?
Yeah.
Right.
So, having talked now about sort of those ancient Near Eastern prophets outside of the
Old Testament, we now turn to the most famous pagan Ancient Near Eastern prophet who
shows up in the Old Testament.
Right.
There's not an Israelite prophet.
Yeah.
That is Baalum the Son of Baalur.
the donkey guy. Right. Right. Turn into a bear. Right.
Despite certain Tokidian similarities. No, no, he's not aware of
here. Not aware of here. So he did kind of turn into a donkey
at a certain point in a way. In a sense. So in the book of
numbers, which I know is everyone's favorite book of the Bible.
people can't get enough of it.
Um, Baylach gets hired by Baylach, the king of the Moabites.
Right?
And Baylach, not to be confused with Baylach,
played by everyone's favorite actor, Clint Howard,
in Star Trek Original Series episode, the Corbamanite maneuver.
Wow!
Wow.
Wow, and see I thought we actually had a request from someone saying
you know, the fact that we titled this episode profit motive that we had to make references
to the deep space.
Yeah, right.
But no, it's the, sorry, Scott Brewer.
I know you're listening.
He referenced original series first.
Way too old school for that.
I worked at a TOS and the Clint Howard reference.
So, appreciate that was Clint Howard's first movie role because he was literally like four
years old or something.
It looks like.
Yes.
Yes, he offers the tron, which looks like orange juice.
Yes, right.
Yeah.
So back to reality.
I'm just going to get hired by, by Baylac, the king of Moab.
And he's hired to curse Israel.
Right.
Yeah.
He says I want you to go
And put the whammy on Israel, right, so they will fail in battle against me.
And does not explain the scientific basis of the whammy.
But it never's 22.
There's probably the most famous episode regarding BAM, which is where he's riding his donkey,
right, and trying to ride over.
on his way to go try and curse his real.
and the angel of the Lord comes and blocks his path,
his path, and Baylon can't see him,
but the donkey can.
The donkey does, yeah.
I mean, could you-
I was gonna say, could you say
and trying to put the whammy on Israel
that he was pushing his luck?
Sorry, I couldn't.
First of all, it's press, press your luck.
Well, okay, okay, press your-
So you even-
I know, I mean, right, well, you know,
it's not as a radio ladies and gentlemen.
I know you could tell you could tell us the joke was not in the notes, you know yeah, yeah
So still going I don't know I have to look that up now. Yeah, they brought it back
Of all the things to bring back Elizabeth Banks hosted now
Anyway
Wow the original series ended in 1986
Yeah, there was that whole controversy with the guy who was
like 200,000, anyway. Now we're really digressing. But there's a documentary about it about the guy who
won like $200,000 on pressure luck. There was a whole scam. Anyway. So, Bailem is writing his donkey.
Donkey sees H.O. Lord Bailem doesn't, right? And so stops and you get this whole thing where he's
like beating the donkey trying to get it to go. And then finally, he sees H.O. Lordm's like oops,
Right. But now that we've talked a little about inches.
in the history of prophecy.
And since before the show we've talked about who the angel of the Lord is.
Here's an example of how this provides some important subtext.
Because what makes Ba'lem a prophet?
Why would someone hire him to co-incure his Israel?
Well, because he has seen and encountered the gods.
Right.
Yeah.
That's why that's the only reason.
The reason.
Right, and so his powers of divine vision are apparently inferior to that of your average riding donkey.
Right, it is real. Right, so that's a deliberate juxtaposition.
Yeah, that the donkey sees God and bail him down.
Yeah, the donkey sees God. The donkey has a better understanding of how the spiritual world works
and how it affects.
physical world, then bail him the famous prophet does.
Right.
So that said, bail has been harder to do a job.
He's a professional of nothing else.
So he goes to try to do it anyway.
And so first he goes to the seven altars
to bail at Curiaf Azot and tries to curse
ends up prophesying blessings for Israel. So he's trying to speak and God keeps putting words in his mouth.
So he's now gone from being sub-donkey level prophet to ventriloquist dummy. Then in chapter 23 of
numbers he goes to the seven altars at PISCA to have another go at it right and so the idea
They're actually build the seven altars of Piscat.
The idea here is that they're offering sacrifices.
Yeah, to track divine attention.
Sort of before each try, right?
So they go to the one place where there are already
these established altars, they offer their sacrifices.
He gives it a go, it doesn't work.
You're like, oh, let's try somewhere else, right?
Maybe this place doesn't have the vibe anymore, right?
The sacred space is not so sacred anymore.
So they go to this other sacred space.
They build seven altars to make their sacrifices.
A tap number two.
to strike number two he had some blessing.
Israel.
And then finally in numbers 24 he goes to Baal Paor,
another high place to bail, third time, not the charm.
And he has a super blessing.
Israel.
And making some important prophecies.
Right.
that actually we're not going to read the whole thing.
But there are a couple of bits that we wanted to highlight.
These are bits that are quoted as prophecies in our hymns, in church that we think about
and talk about.
And we may not realize that these came out of the mouth of Bailum when he was trying to
curse Israel.
Yeah.
That ball pay or right.
He was a demon worshipper.
But yes, so he said these very famous lines in numbers 24 verse 9.
be crouched.
He lay down like a lion and like a lioness who will rouse him up or sometimes it gets translated. I think lions well
Right
Well, yeah, and while this is this is picking up on imagery from
The prophecy concerning Judah the tribe of Judah right in the testament of Jacob in Genesis 48
Right
So this is doubt tailing with that. Yeah, and then and then another one probably more famous
Number 2417, a star shall come out of Jacob.
and a scepter shall rise out of Israel.
I mean these are Messianic prophecies about Jesus coming out of the mouth of this
this guy.
Yeah.
Now given he's operating in some vitriloquist dummy at the time.
Right.
But yeah he also pronounces doom on the amulacates so he does curse somebody.
Yeah.
Curses of giants.
So yeah, but notice though how prophetically
those things go together. The coming of the Messiah and the doom of the giants here are
in invalem's prophecy are sort of wrapped up together. And those two things continue to
be wrapped up together throughout the old and into the New Testament. We had to talk about
giants at some point. It's Lord of Spirits.
So now somebody may have had the ding-ding go off or reset into this.
time, this third and final time that he tried to curse Israel, he was at Balpeor. So you
may remember some other stuff that went down there, some bad stuff. And that was that there
were these groups of Moabite, usually called priestesses or just women in Boga-Rize English
translations. They're actually essentially shrine prostitutes for this high place. At
ball of peor they seduce the number of the Israelites that
results in this plague breaking forth in the camp.
We've talked about Phineas or Phineas or Peenihas before.
We'll put that into it, I'll show you before.
But importantly, right, so there's these two sort of dots.
Dot one is, this is where Bayla makes its third attempt
to curse Israel and fails.
Dot two is, there's a apostasy by Israel at the same place.
You might expect that at some point in rabbinic
and or Christian tradition, they would connect those two dots and say that
Baelum was involved in the apostasy. But you don't have to wait for that
because those dots are connected already in
Numbers chapter 31 and in Joshua 13. Yeah. Right.
Where essentially Baelum having tried three times in fails
to curse Israel, right? The idea is, well I can't curse them
as long as
they're following their God, right? But if I can get them to betray their God, because he's looking at it as their God must be too powerful for me, right? And for my God's.
But if I can get them on the wrong side of their God, they'll end up cursed, right?
Right, which is so this is not entirely wrong. Right. So he does he does understand some sort of spiritual technology here.
Well, you know, their God is too powerful for my God to curse them.
Maybe I can get their God to curse them.
Right?
I believe they love the wrong side of it.
And so that's how it's then portrayed there in the Old Testament.
And that idea of Baalum also gets picked up in the New Testament.
In 2 Peter chapter 2, in the Book of Jude, in Revelation chapter 2, where Baalum is presented
this sort of this archetype of the heritake, right?
of the false teacher who arises within the church,
and who leads people into apostasy,
leads them away from Christ, leads them
back under the curse.
They're analogized to Bailem the son of Bohr,
he becomes the archetype of that.
Yeah.
But interestingly,
He did still...
make those veseasic prophecy. Right, which are quoted and you know,
affirmed it. Right, yeah. So, um, and, and it's not that he apostles didn't know
about that, right, when they were using him as this architect, right? So they
didn't have to say every word that comes out of the mouth that these false
features is a lie.
Right.
Say Paul,
about people who are preaching the gospel for false motives, it says, well at least the
gospel is getting preached.
So it's not sort of all or nothing.
The fact that the prophecy came out of Balom's mouth or the donkey's mouth, does it make
it false?
the fact that a prophecy came out of the mouse also does it make them true.
Right. Right exactly. Right. It did not make that a holy donkey. Right. I mean, yeah, sometimes God makes use of people
even against their will without endorsing them, you know. Right. Yeah. Which is very reassuring as a priest.
Yes. Thank God.
And then, you know, just another note, a phylo, a Alexandria who we've brought up on the show before,
I get a fight's bail on his own wizard.
Your own wizard bail?
Which I just think is kind of cool.
But even cooler than that is that there was an inscription found in Der Aula, which is
now in Jordan, but which was in Moab.
the description is from the late
9th or early 8th century BC.
Yeah.
And the inscription is in a wall, but it's written in a wall.
So these iron age buildings were generally made of stone.
And then the inside and sometimes the outside were then plastered.
Okay.
was sort of primitive plaster, right?
And...
While the plaster was wet, they would paint essentially, use pigment to paint or write in
the plaster.
So basically fresco?
Right, sort of.
Although a lot cruder than the fresco should make you.
Yeah, right, right.
It's a bit history.
Right, and basic.
Right, right.
Off it it was writing rather than elaborate painting.
In this case, it's writing.
It's an inscription.
makes it kind of mysterious because it's unclear why someone would want this on the wall of their house.
But anyway, but it does date from that time. We've got firm dating on it. This is within what was Moab,
and it refers to Bala Am the son of Bayor. Right? So literally the same name. Bala Am the son of Bayor.
Yeah.
And it identifies him as a prophet.
of Oshchar, the S-H-T-A-R, who was the wife of Kimosh, the Moon God, who was the primary
deity of the Mawmites.
Right.
Is this the same guy as Shemish?
No.
Shemish is the Sun God.
got okay. Alright alright. So
Ashtar is generally seen, I mean linguistically, to be a version of Astarte, who is Bales' wife.
So this is sort of the goddess figure, your usual goddess figure coming out of Canaanite religion.
So that's who he is, and also a god who we're not sure who it is.
So we only have consonants, and the consonants are schg-n-er.
So sugar, I don't know.
or Shogre or Shogre, I mean there's lots of ways it could go who could have been vocalized, right?
So that is a secondary God maybe in some way related to
Ashtar and then also the gods of Shade which may be a collective name for those two or
Something else right that we're not exactly sure
and
this bail of
instead of Bayore, exact same name. It said to have brought a prophecy from that goddess saying
that that goddess, he had had a dream that that goddess was coming to destroy the earth and bring
about everlasting life. Yeah, that's a cheery thing to put on your wall. Yeah, so I guess it was like,
don't worry, be happy, right? You three could be married because tomorrow we die. Yeah. Live
black world. Hey, I don't.
I don't know.
It's the live laugh, love of its time.
Eight nights on TBC.
I have a great time because endless night.
But what it shows us is this Balam Son of Boar
was some kind of known figure.
Yeah, I mean this is still,
how many centuries later or whatever
that he's being talked about.
Yeah.
He's some kind of known figure.
And a lot of people at church with this
is him being some kind of folk hero.
I think that may be a little bit of presentism, right?
Like comparing him to Paul Bunyan.
Right.
Um,
Avinous sentence.
Um, so there's much of an assotance.
Let's say that's going.
You're saying Paul Bunyan.
Is it real?
Um,
It's just very tall and dutch, right?
He's not.
Babies real.
Babies, the blue ox is real.
Yeah, the bull of heaven.
Right.
Um,
but Mahima.
So.
But yeah, so he that's probably a reading a little too much back in terms of the idea of a folk era like that, but he is clearly some kind of major figure there and their religious past too.
So, and this is in Moa, but of course it's the Moa by King and numbers who who hires him.
Right, so this is to be to be really presentest about it.
This is
like a special guest appearance, right?
This is like a crossover episode of the numbers.
This is like when Mork showed up on Happy Days,
where Baylon shows up,
part of the story of Israel.
I had almost forgotten about that.
Wow, we've raged far and wide in this episode so far.
Yeah.
You know, when we don't have like an engineer sitting on us,
This gets weird, man.
I'm in real life because I'm engineering.
Yeah, right.
It's OK.
So, finally, in our first app here,
in talking about extrovertical prophecy,
we need to say a little bit about prophecy in Greece,
Greek prophecy is really going to verge into Greco-Roman.
How has it seen sort of no circles?
So in Greek prophecy, oracles are way more...
common than yellowers. Right. Yeah. Because there's I'm sure there's more money in being an
Oracle. Like they're coming to you. I know. I mean, it's a little cynical. But I mean,
they're coming to you, right? Looking for answers. Well, a lot of the Oracle's also were slaves
in virtually or literally like in acts, right? But yeah. But I mean, Oracle Delphine was virtually
So, and Delphi, the work of Delphi Curses is the most famous one, probably.
But there were oracles all over the Greek and Roman world.
Do practices.
So this is possession.
Remember the Oracle Delphi was believed to be possessed by Apollo.
Apollo was generally seen to be the God connected with prophecy.
We talk about them a lot.
I think, you know, even people who haven't read Nietzsche are under this whole Nietzsche's distinction
between the Apollonians.
and being a see-and-it's kind of infected, everybody's feeling Apollo.
But Helios is the God of the Sun, right?
So Apollo, there is a connection to the Sun, but Apollo is more a lightbringer figure,
right?
That's why he's connected to philosophy, right?
A bringer of light and wisdom.
So he's lightbringer, more light, the devil.
Yeah, right?
That kind of lightbringer.
In the Old Testament.
So, and if you look at, I know we've mentioned this before,
that actually one of the four horsemen of the apocalypse
is actually an old, a moldy old kid and I got,
Refish, who is, was depicted as an archer.
Now this is actually referred to in the,
in the psalm, right, the arrows that fly by day,
by redarts of the Evil One.
Please.
a refesh references. So he was a sort of demonic being this canon at God who had these
plague arrows. And the earliest, most archaic pictures of Apollo, we have are similar.
He has plague arrows. So he seems to have been in a simulation from the Near East of
that type of idea. So Apollo was a much darker figure than we give him credit for being
ironically
being the lightbringer
yeah but he's also the
associated with prophecy. In terms of the shatter type of prophet, who shows up
with a message, the most famous one is easily Treesius, at least in terms of
texts we still have, that have been passed down to us, who was associated with
Apollo, and who was blind. We'll talk about how we became blind in just a
Yeah, so Treesia shows up a bunch of
places. But he was not to be the son of an infant and human, so we've got some nephilim
action going on there. Wow, so there's this nature spirit and a human who produce him.
He's from an associate with the city of Bebes. So he has this, what makes him a prophet is
that he has this encounter with Zeus and Hera, sort of direct encounter with the gods.
sort of initiates them as a problem.
But then he kind of gets in trouble with Hera because he sees two snakes
copulating and
gets grossed out by it and kills them
so
Hera and Athena for that matter
When you look at their cults in Greece are constantly connected to serpent imagery. Yeah, right?
Right.
There were snakes in certain places that were sacred to Hera.
Athena is often depicted with a snake. So there's a whole woman in a snake, snake giving the
woman wisdom motif in Greek stories that gets really creepy when you think about Genesis
chapter 3. But so when Herregates mad because he killed these snakes, Herra turns him into
woman. This again, right? And three
Now a woman decides to make the best of it and becomes a priestess of Hera and gets married and has some kids
They did change back after a while like seven years or something. Yes, he remains a woman for seven years
It gets changed back into a man
And then
He has the misfortune because again. He's having these encounters with the gods all the time, right because he's a prophet
He sees a thing.
make him taking a bath. That's good. Walks into the bathroom. Oh no. Get struck blind. Right.
Right. So this is how he becomes the blind prophet, Treesius. So you get that kind of blind
C-er motif that you were referring to with own. Yeah. Right. This idea that you sort of sacrifice,
Again, your ability to fit in with an interact with the material world.
in order to instead see and interact with the spiritual world.
And also the idea that again these encounters with the gods, in his case,
are all sort of destructive to hit.
Right. Right.
They all exact this horrible sort of toll on his humanity.
What if there is since he's only had human in the first place?
So then he shows up a bunch of famous places.
He shows up in the Odyssey.
And...
In the Odyssey, the interesting thing about him
is it's his shade.
It's his spirit.
He's dead.
Yeah, that shows up in Hades when Odysseus goes there
to talk to Achilles and he sacrifices the black goats
and pours the blood into the pit
and the shades come and drink the blood.
Not creepy at all.
But before even, the other shades have to come
and drink the blood like to reinvigorate themselves.
Like Achilles, we can talk to them.
Which is just a wandering out.
Hey guys, what's up?
Yeah, Teresa's shade is sort of of a different category.
It's still there in Hades, but there's sort of shades
of the refa heave here, right?
He's kind of quasi-divine.
And so even his shade seems to be
in this sort of different category, albeit in Hades.
The Goth Club that is Hades.
He's in a sort of different state.
He also shows up with the story of King
cadmous, he shows up in edifice Rex, edifice the king, to tell edifice, hey oopsie, killed
your dad married your mom, not cool. Which leads to edifice gouging out his eyes, sort
of imitation of Turyceus with his blindness, right?
Because now the truth has been...
or if you don't do it, I'm not sure how you can't see anymore.
Wow.
So yeah, so we've given you here kind of the outlines of the first half of what sort of the
profit is in the pagan world sort of surrounding the scriptures.
Hopefully, you've seen the through line that this is sort of a dark thing.
This involves madness, this involves mutilation, this involves sort of...
and destructive as the interaction of humans with these spirits.
And so in our second half, we're going to turn to the old test of it,
where we will get a little bit of a different picture of prophecy,
not completely dissimilar but different.
A little bit of a breather, as it were from all this weird dark stuff.
All right, we're going to take a break and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part.
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Welcome in gifts.
Sacrifice in the Bible and Christian Life by Jeremy Davis.
You'll find surprising answers in this book.
You'll learn that...
The Pope had a very different significance for ancient people than it does for us today.
You'll hear how it drifted away from this ancient significance into a fundamentally different
meaning in our modern world.
You'll discover how old testament sacrifices were gifts from the heart only tangentially
related to killing and death.
You'll see in Christ's cross the ultimate gift that ushers us into communion with God,
you'll find inspiration.
to offer your own gifts alongside Christs, inviting God into your life.
Welcome in gifts, sacrifice in the Bible and Christian life.
Now available in paperback, eBook and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com
Yeah, that's our theme in metal. That was sent in by the listener Rob. So thank you, Rob,
very much for that. I know you were trying to get our attention.
I'll leave you hanging for a while.
In terms of that commercial, was that father Jeremy doing the...
Yeah, that was father Jeremy doing the reading his own book there.
I don't do great libraries.
That was a better library than I do.
you. Oh right. But it came off to me as a little dry. So I want to tell people, even if that came
off to you as a little dry, that's a really good book and you should buy it. Yeah, Father Steven did
did endorse the book. So I endorse this product. Yeah. I'm Commander Shepard. No.
Yeah, I haven't I haven't read it yet, but I mean, it looks like he's, you know, a lot of the stuff
of the people like about some of the stuff we do.
talk about is in there. You know, just focusing on this one topic, though, on sacrifice.
So I'm looking forward to reading it myself. I haven't read it yet.
Yes, I will not have to write a book on sacrifice because he covered it.
Wow, there you go, everybody. So, yes. So by all means, get it.
Yes. Nice.
All right. Well, we're in the second half.
Second half despite what you despite what you I'm not sure
what that sound was, but we're live.
It's terribly mysterious.
Yes, yes.
Despite what you heard from the voice of Steve
as we were going to the break, we're not taking calls.
But I am monitoring the chat on our YouTube stream
and on Facebook.
So a couple of people have asked questions that basically
we'll just simply say.
Yeah, they're, oh, well, it's funny.
There is a fun little blip during the first maybe 15, 20 minutes
soap.
where if you actually sort of watch the video feed,
instead of like the generic banner,
you could see the furniture at the Chesterton studio
and people were talking about like,
what could this mean?
Why are we looking at furniture, you know?
And so that was a lot of fun.
Well, you know why that happened?
We were talking about divination.
Right, right, that became the discussion.
It must be a sign.
Why is this chair at that angle?
Yeah.
Who can interpret this for us?
Yes.
And also we received one little bit of review
from a gentleman who is unhappy with the number
of Star Trek references we've made so far.
So.
What?
How few?
We could make more.
I think it's too many for him.
You can under advise me.
What do you mean one?
I don't know.
What did a half?
Yeah.
Well, here we are.
But, you know, this is the show.
So all right.
Well, back to prop.
but now we're looking at
Prophets of the Old Testament prophets of Israel, right rather than this dark freaky bizarre pagan stuff
It gets a little freaky sometimes but not curious freaky is what we're just talking about, right?
So yeah, so we're gonna start sort of with
Titles again, right sort of the Hebrew Titles
And
that are used to refer to profits.
The main one and the one that people know,
they don't know any others, right,
is Navi or Navi-Geeam being the plural.
Sometimes, so that V sound is actually a vape.
So it could be pronounced as a B or a B,
or a B,
Yeah, on context again.
vocalization. So Navi or Navi, Navi-E, or Navi-E, and that word comes into Hebrew from
Akkadian, from the Akkadian Naboo, which means to call out or to yell. So again,
even the back of your head, this Greek idea of Karigma, of a message that is called out.
out.
So that's gonna be the primary context in which prophecy is talked about.
So we don't really see a regular prophecy, right?
Possession-type prophecy.
right i mean you get you get like you get like david inquiring of the
should I do this? You know, especially like should I go out to this battle, whatever
in God saying, don't do that or yes or do that? But there's not, like you said, there's
not oracles who are being possessed and God speaking through them kind of thing.
Right. There is a phenomenon, especially in Joshua and Judges, at
person 2 Samuel or person 2nd Kingdoms, of Holy Spirit possession. Yeah. Right.
using those
terms probably freaks people out but deal with it.
That's what everybody called it.
Where it's usually translated as something like the Holy Spirit comes upon someone like
one of the judges.
Yeah, not that they were filled with the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, not that they were filled with the Holy Spirit, which is this very sort of saintly
kind of image.
But yeah, like you said, comes upon or rushes upon.
Right, and then usually they kill a whole lot of people.
But it's they do something. It's not that they're sort of possessed and a voice comes out of their right.
Yeah.
And you know, someone speaks in. So that particular type of prophecy, you don't really see the Old Testament.
But you do see that. And there is a certain affinity in that Holy Spirit possession phenomenon in the frenzy idea in the right.
there.
But the idea there is more that the actions that the person is taking in that case are the actions of God not their own.
Right. So like they're meeting out God's judgment.
Right. It's not their own vengeance or what have you. Right.
It's the idea that's trying to be conveyed by that. Right.
Right. So that's a different thing than sort of a rackular possession.
So that said, Navi is not the only term that's used for profits.
The actual earlier term that we find in the oldest parts of the Old Testament are there
two terms.
Jose or Roa, both of which literally mean a seer, someone who sees something, right?
And so that again gives you this visionary idea.
Right, the idea that they have this direct encounter
encounter with God, and then the second piece,
they've been given a message to deliver.
Yeah.
There's also the feminine form Nevillea,
which is used both for a prophetess,
if you want to go walking James, a female prophet,
like some of like
Debra in the book of Judges, but is also used for the wife of a prophet.
It's sort of a title by association just like we have.
Right, which literally means like priestess.
Right.
Literally means female priest.
He's used for the priest.
So the same thing was true with prophets.
And so a good example of that in the Old Testament is Isaiah.
Right, God tells him
to go into the prophetess, right?
And that's not some woman who's not his wife,
that it's his wife.
Yeah, right, right.
And have a son and name him Marishallah Hashbaz.
Right.
God would not tell him to go and be with a woman
that's not his wife.
Right, that's not something God says to do.
Right, go to the prophetess, prophetess,
definite article, meaning specific one, your wife.
Yours, yeah.
Right.
And that's a name of Marishallah Hashbaz.
and uh
We actually read that, and I think two points
in the liturgical year, and let me just say,
people who translated that from the Greek
so you don't have Mahershalo Hashbaz
and they put in something like,
David runs quickly to divide the spoils or something.
It's not working, dude.
Mahershalo Hashbaz.
There's an actor now that that's his name.
That's his name, I can't remember what his last name is,
but he goes by something shorter,
but that is his actual first name.
Yeah.
It's a person.
I mean, Isaiah's son, I'm just saying, throwing it out there.
Baptism will name and come up with one.
So these are the terms, right?
One of the most prominent ways, though,
that we talk about and use that term of Navi or Navi-E, right?
is to refer to a division of the Old Testament.
Okay. Right. So,
classically the
the Hebrew Bible or the Christian test of it is divided into three parts. There's the Torah
right there's the
Navi him
the prophets and then the Ketu beam which is the writings
Right sort of the rest of the stuff. Right. These are the traditional Hebrew terms for these divisions in the Bible right
Those are the Hebrew ones, Torah, Navi and Ketuim. That's why you'll sometimes hear
Jewish folks and the occasional evangelicals trying to sound cool
refer to it as the Tanakh. Right, yes, which is like the first letters T and A. Yeah. Yeah.
So, but so that being central division, right?
is the prophets, right? And you'll hear sort of the scriptures referred to the New Testament as the law and the prophets,
right, which is a translation of the Torah and the prophets, right?
sort of cover everything, because people are still debating which of the writings were in and which ones were out, right?
They weren't really debating it, just different places that received different collections of writings.
So they're considered important dating at that time.
So the
The prophets, that division of the Hebrew Bible or the Christian testament, is generally
considered to consist of.
On one hand, Joshua Judges wrote the books of Samuel, the books of kings, or the books
of kingdoms.
And then also, on the other hand, the sort of writing prophets, Isaiah, Jeremiah and the
Jeremiah material.
Ezekiel, and then the book of the 12, which I've now discovered a lot of people haven't
heard that term before.
The book of the 12 is what you've probably heard referred to more commonly in modern English
Bibles as the minor prophets.
Right.
So it was bound together as a single collection, as that was called?
All one scroll.
One scroll, yeah.
Yeah.
So it's interesting about that.
that you gave is that normally, at least in English, when we think about prophetic books,
we would think about books like Isaiah, or Jeremiah, but Joshua, which is a series of wars
and so forth, judges, these are just sort of narratives.
Is that prophecy, thus say it the Lord, etc.?
Alright, so yeah, this is this is
where are German friends, once again rear their ugly heads in the 19th century.
Right? So a lot of English Vibles, you will not find the prophets including all these
books as a division, instead you find historical books and prophetic books. Right? These have
been divided. And those books with Joshua and Judges and Ruth and kingdoms, those are considered
quote unquote historical books that are telling us about history.
history. And then the other books are books of prophecy. And that even gets skewed into
this is all stuff about the future. Right? Yeah. Yeah. So let me, but so these are genre
categories that we're putting on to them versus the ones that the people who received them
initially, how they understood. Yeah. And not just initially until modern time. Yeah.
Sure, right, right, right?
Even when these are distinguished like by church fathers and stuff, it's the former prophets and the latter prophets.
Yeah, just a chronological distinction.
Right.
But it's still all considered prophets and so,
this is the problem we've talked about at length now on the show, the modern view of history intruding itself into how we read
the script and the old testament in particular.
Right? And
makes a big difference whether you read the book of Joshua as a prophetic book, as a book
of prophecy, or as a history book.
Yeah.
Especially if you have a modern idea of history.
Right.
Yeah, it's the story of a people, which is the traditional view of history, versus a
reconstructed narrative of events based on evidence.
Right.
Prophecy, where prophecy comes out.
talk about this a little bit when we talked about apocalyptic again. Prophecy is presenting
this divine perspective, so it's not objective. It's not claiming to be objective. The
book of Joshua is making no more claim to be objective than Isaiah is. The author of
the book of Joshua is presented to us in Scripture as speaking for God. This is God
I'm speaking.
about these events. Just as in Isaiah, God is speaking about events. So there's not a fundamental
difference between the prophetic writer of the book of Judges, talking about these elements
of the history of the tribes of Israel, and Isaiah coming and talking about what was happening
in his day, or what was soon to happen.
happened or what had happened in the past. Right? This is all
presenting God's perspective, God's interpretation, it's
presenting the meaning of events, not just presenting events
and making the claim that those events actually happened in
exactly this way. Right. Right. Exactly. So saying they didn't
happen. Right. But it's saying something about them and about
their meaning. Yeah. And how does this function within the
community.
Right. Well, I was just presenting a series of facts.
Yeah, right exactly.
Right.
So, yeah, that is very important in terms of how we approach those books.
And those are also considered books of prophecy.
Those are also considered a message from God, right?
And if we consider that history of the people was understood at that time to be,
this is who we are, this is where we came from, this is where we're going,
Then, this is God telling Israel.
This is who you are. This is where you came from. This is where you're going. Yeah. Right.
And that's what that prophetic understanding. So even though,
those are the prophetic books. Those texts are designated as the prophets.
Prophecy doesn't start there. You've got prophecy, obviously, obviously to most people, in the Torah.
Right, right.
So, I mean, Moses, right?
But even before Moses, really the first person who's
presented as a prophet directly by the text of the Torah.
Because I know somebody's going to bring up
Enek, but Enek doesn't say anything
in the book of Genesis.
Anyway.
Yeah, he's just sort of mentioned.
Yeah.
He doesn't himself say to me, you've got
to get the book of Enek for that, right?
Let's start.
but so Abraham is really the person whose first percentage is a prophet.
Yeah, and I mean the first major thing we know about him is that God says get up and leave.
Yeah, God appears to him and says get up and leave.
believe which I mean this is you know this one of these basic sort of elements of prophecy
someone who's kind of outside of the social order
And he's living in Err, the greatest city of the time,
the civilization and God tells him to leave
and go someplace else.
Right, so he's removed from the social order
by this experience of having this directed,
and he has many of them open, of course, of his life.
Yeah, right.
Where he sees God, stands in talks to God,
has these direct encounters with God,
unmediated, right?
And of course, we've talked about how this is Christ, right?
in our
in our series on this. But so he has these direct encounters, direct encounters with God,
and is directed to do things, to go places and do things. And so this is really the first
verse that he's presented as a prophet in that sense. We're told Enoch has this some kind of
direct encounter with God, but we're not told in the text of Genesis what comes of that. But you
can certainly understand why after the fact, people reading that Genesis was say, oh,
eat it must have been a prop.
Right. Right. Based on that. So this continues, right, with his, we don't really have anything
very clear like this with Isaac. Jacob certainly. Yeah, multiple visions.
Seize God multiple times and wrestles with him and sees the Zyra, right?
because it can be the letter.
Yeah, at Beth L. Right.
the house of God. So he has these direct encounters. But then we see a little bit of a shift
when we get to Joseph. Jacob's son, who the narrative follows because Joseph does not have
as is recorded, these direct encounters instead he has dreams and interprets the dreams of
of Barrow.
Right. And he's embedded within civilization, although he is still kind of an outsider on some level.
Right. He's brought in as a slave. He's a Hebrew. But, but he's, but it's interesting, you know,
to look at the pattern with his life, right, is that he's he's not only brought in as a slave,
but it's when he's in prison that he's called up as this answerer as an interpreter.
But because ultimately,
God is moving him into position there to save his brothers, right?
To save his family.
He's going to have to be sort of reinvented,
unlike his father and grandfather and great grandfather,
reinvented in society.
He's going to be coming to official in Egypt.
And so he doesn't have these direct encounters.
God still communicates with them.
Right? God still has his relationship with him,
but it's more mediated than it was with Abraham.
with Abraham who's going to go live as an element.
right right or Jacob who lives as a no-man right so there's there's a there's a
shift there for that purpose and then when we get to Moses in Exodus right and
Moses has the directed counters again with God in the in the burning bush right and
then later on it's out in the wilderness right he doesn't see God while he's in
Pharaoh's court. Right? He gets pulled back out of
civilization, right, and is living in the desert when he has these direct encounters. And
he then sort of becomes the paradigm for what a prophet is because he has these extended
experiences, direct experiences of God, right? 40 days on top of his side, I 40 days and
40 nights of the divine counsel.
Face to face as a man speaks to his friend. I mean, yeah, and then right, going into the
the 10th meeting, right?
And that, right?
So he's...
sort of on this ongoing basis in a way that no one before that and really
Nobody after that the old testament has right
Just this sort of ongoing basis and it's not just you know me saying hey
Quantity wise he's the paradigmatic prophet right the promise if the end of Deuteronomy is that God's gonna send them a prophet like
Moses yeah, he's treated in this to theonomy sense about right
This is this is
what the prophet of Yahweh is going to be like, he's going to be like Moses. So yeah, so
you can see that there's a modulation here from what we saw outside of Israel already,
just with these prophets in the Torah. So on one hand, yes, these figures who have these direct
encounters with God. It does do something to you. Right? It does pull them out of society.
It does make them function at a different level.
It does realize it does remove,
that make them kind of an outsider figure.
But that is not done in this destructive way.
Yeah, you don't see them like losing their minds
and harming themselves.
And yeah, it's very different.
There's, and, and, and, I mean, I would say,
well, why is it different?
It's because they're having an encounter with...
the God of the universe who created them and loves them versus demons, right?
I mean, that's a big difference because the one you're encountering and having a
communion with is very, very different. Right, right. And so there's
continuities and discontentities. But the discontentities there are significant and
import. Right. Right. And they continue. You know, they have wives and children. Right.
they have, right? So it's not that they're made something inhuman or subhuman or nonhuman
and there's a weird, liminal nonhuman space now. But that they're now a human who lives
and acts and understands things differently because they have this different perspective now.
Yeah, right on the things in the world.
So we get to as we have prophets.
coming to Israel. And people come and say, I have a message from Yahweh to God of Israel.
We get to a point where people need to discern who really is coming bearing a message from
Yahweh the God of Israel, and who's not or a liar or a grifter.
Yeah, a problem.
that still holds today.
Yeah, really?
I know.
You want to believe the best of everyone.
Yes.
You know me.
Paulianne, I'm just teasing you.
So,
so there has to be an understanding of what makes someone.
And so, the,
we've talked already about
they're being these sort of two pieces.
But the first and foremost piece we kind of get spelled out in Jeremiah
About the fact that that direct encounter with Yahweh the God of Israel
Is necessary
Because if whatever this message is is something you've divine
We're choice intentional right that means it's not from Yahweh the God of Israel right
Right.
If it's something you've written.
the tea leaves or you've you know worked out for yourself. Wait, I took every eighth
letter of the Torah. Are you saying the Bible code? The Bible code is not. Oh man. And you know how
I know this? How do you know this? Because if you use the same algorithm on Mobe Dick,
on page, I think it's like 173 or something, it says there are no codes in the Bible,
but there are cones and mobility days.
Nice.
I thought there was gonna be a Patrick Stewart.
thing but but no no no no we've already gone to that well okay we've already gone to that well
if I were to do another mobi dick thing it would be gone oh anyway yeah so that that direct
encounter over again so it's kind of ways of divining right flipped open my Bible and it opened
to this page, whatever else, that's sort of the key thing.
And that's spelled out in, so in, in,
in,
Jeremiah, there's this contest between Jeremiah and these other people who claim to be prophets
of Yahweh.
Yeah.
And they kind of have the upper hand because Jerusalem's under siege by the Babylonians
and Jeremiah is showing up, actually from the God of Israel, saying, yeah, you guys are
doomed, man.
Not what anyone wants to hear.
Right.
And they're saying, you traitor, right?
these other so-called profits of the government.
out of Israel are saying, no, no, we're good, man. Everything's good. God's going to deliver us,
right? And so God Himself through Jeremiah sort of lays out what's required.
Yeah. Okay. So this is Jeremiah chapter 23 verses 18 through 22. For who among them has stood in
the counsel of the Lord to see and to hear his word? Or who has paid attention to his word and
listened. Behold the storm of the Lord.
Wrath has gone forth, a whirling tempest it will burst upon the head of the wicked.
The anger of the Lord will not turn back until he has executed and accomplished the intense
of his heart.
In the latter days you will understand it clearly.
I did not send the prophets yet they ran, I did not speak to them yet they prophesied,
but if they had stood in my counsel then they would have proclaimed my words to my people,
and they would have turned them from their evil way and from the evil of their deeds.
I think it's...
it's worth pointing out here, it starts out,
who is stood in the counsel Lord to see and to hear his word?
It's not just words, it's the word,
because you don't see a word, you know,
you see the word, the word of Yahweh,
the word of the word Christ himself, but yes, so.
Yeah.
And so when you're standing in the counsel of Yahweh,
the person who you see in here is the word,
The Barrier Ware.
the Word of God. See, previous episode. Yes.
But so you have here those two pieces. You have piece one, you have to be in the divine counsel.
You have to have this direct encounter with God, like Moses had.
Right? Like the Remus prophets have had.
And then you get sent on a mission.
And so you get this inverted there in verse 21.
I did not send them, but they ran.
They did just show up. They came running.
They were very eager, right?
And he did not speak to them yet.
Here they come with some message they got someone, right?
And so we see that second piece,
especially laid out, if you read like Isaiah,
especially, Isaiah has the vision, right?
The Lord, and then there's the whole dialogue
who shall we send and who will go for us, right?
and say that's the fear I am, send me.
the us being the council meeting there with the chairman of the
serum from. And so that being sent, then being sent out with
this message. And so again, as we're just reiterating in Jeremiah,
remember when it says the word of Yahweh, the word of the Lord,
De Barrio, came to blank. This isn't a whisper looting in the land.
Yeah.
Again.
Because this is being contrasted with people kind of defining it or figuring out or working off hints, right?
This is that is the bad kind
The kind of work stolen here is you see and
Here the word of the Lord. It's clear. Right. So this is the word of love. This is a person
Showing up and talking to them, right? And so this is the word who say John tells us became flesh. This is Christ
Right coming and speaking to these people right or they are brought into the the divine counsel and Christ is there speaking to that right
And they see him and hear him and interact with them right and so
We have to hear disambiguate a little
Between a false prophet which is what we're talking about here. This is a false prophet
This is someone who presents themselves as a prophet, but who is not a prophet? Yeah, right
versus
for example the prophets of Bale. Yeah, you know I just wanted to break in actually we just got a
pretty relevant question from Facebook this is from I think it's that's shocking. I know I know
this is from Facebook. I think it's pronounced Evan EV O N. So she writes this so when King saw
prophesied with the prophets was he just possessed by the Holy Spirit or was he actually counted
to the prophets.
That's her question.
It's a good question.
Yes.
So, he is an example.
We're going to get into this a little bit more in just a minute with this as a specific
example.
But so, Saul, when that happens, Saul is looking for David, right?
David's on the land.
And he goes to this dwelling place where Samuel is, Samuel is sort of the...
and Judge of Israel at this time, but he lives in this community of prophets, the sort of village of prophets,
where he has his own altar, by the way, and offers sacrifices.
And what the text says is that this place is so sort of thick with the Holy Spirit,
with the spirit of God, with the prophets living there, right?
And this is such a holy place.
this has become such a sacred space that when Saul goes there looking for David, thinking
David might be hiding there.
As soon as he enters the place, he sort of has this encounter with the Spirit.
And we tend to think, hey, if you suddenly had this directed counter with God, right,
Thank you.
That would be this wonderful ecstasy, right or this joyous moment, right?
But you don't actually see that anywhere even with the prophets in the Old Testament.
Right when when Moses sees the Burning Bush, he kind of freaks out.
Isaiah, what he has his vision, he's standing in the divine counsel.
Basically curses.
He's like, I'm blanked, right?
right.
Right.
He's not done for.
done. Right. That's a nice bowler eyes way of you know. Whoa is me for I am a simple man. Yeah.
But um and so that's why right to come into the presence of God is to suddenly become very much
aware of your lack of holiness. Yeah. Right. And so with Saul at this point in his life when the Holy
Spirit has left him in an unclean spirit has entered him. Right.
Right? It becomes sort of this almost violent encounter where he strips naked and he's
thrashing around on the ground. Yeah. Right? And it seems more like one of these pagan
prophets have to get encounter. Right? And then what we see with the Hebrew prophets,
but it's because of who Saul is at the time. Yeah. Right? It solves a lot more like
bail on than he is like Samuel at that point.
Yeah, that's that's a great
question.
And she just informed me that her name is pronounced Ivan, which I've never seen I spelled that way EVOM
So I learned something new today you can spell the spelling police man. I'm not
Spelling changes
It just does yeah, but I mean if you if you spell it with a Y you've still you've gone with a Y then
Poor kids in the back of the line there coming in for recess every day
You don't need that. That's true a medical order. That's true
Um.
This is a kid named Zika or something.
I mean, my name starts with an A, so I've always been somewhere.
Somewhere. Yeah.
I'm privileged.
Privilege. Exactly.
I'm proud of yourself.
I know.
Um, so alphabetically privileged.
Um, so.
All right.
So yeah, so yeah, false profits and bail profit.
Yeah, like this is another issue.
So the bail profits, right?
Or false profits.
They're really profits of bail.
Yeah
They really have this spiritual relationship with this, what we would call a demonic spirit.
Whereas these false prophets are people who are not prophets at all, but who claim to be.
That distinction gets blurred by modern folks who want to say, well, Bale doesn't exist.
for they're essentially the same boat, right?
They're just making it up, right?
But.
But the kind of experience we've been talking about that these pagan prophets had, is it
made up?
Yeah.
Someone doesn't go into like a fever and ecstasy and emasculate themselves physically.
Right.
Imagine error.
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
Like what are two crazy people might do that, but you don't get this sort of sustained
institution of that kind of thing.
unless there's some kind of results that people are...
actually experienced I know about martial apple white but still right you don't
have that going on over centuries and I would submit there's probably something
demonic going on with martial apple white too so there is there is the heaven's
gate guy by the way everybody if you don't know who that is yeah yeah you
don't know who martial apple white yeah yeah I mean people don't just sit around
watching documentaries about cold-sul-day
Seriously?
In between episodes of Star Trek?
So I don't do it all day.
But I do sometimes do that.
Yeah.
Right.
So, these are two different things.
And so, and this is important to distinguish also because, and we've even commented on this
on the show before, there are folks among some of some groups of our Protestant friends who
get a fire's prop.
or as being able to prophesy, right?
And as we've said before,
although I don't know if it got through before,
we're not saying those people are like demon possessed, right?
Like they're not, they're not like bail prophets, right?
They're not like, we're not saying they're like
martial apple white, right?
We're not trying to draw that comparison, right?
But someone can be self-deluded.
Right, right.
And be a false prophet in this sense we're talking about.
Right.
They might even think they're legitimately a prophet.
They may think that the message that they've intuitive or however they believe they've
gotten it, right, came to them in a dream, whatever.
They may believe that that is from the Lord, right.
And it may not be.
Right.
And that makes them a false prophet.
and spiritually deluded, right?
And spiritual delusions do come, right?
Those are not good things, right?
Spiritual delusions don't come from God, right?
They come from somewhere else, right?
Okay, disobbiguating my former comments of the show
to try to clarify them.
But you enter into this messy space here because,
Bye.
The Quran, for example, is so clear on what is supposed to happen to false prophets, which
is namely the first time they say something that they claim comes from Yahweh, the God of
Israel, that doesn't, and it becomes apparent that that did not come from Yahweh, the God
of Israel.
They're stoned to death.
Right.
They get executed.
And so we are not for the record advocating, stoning anyone to death.
it.
no matter how much they prophesied that Donald Trump would already be president again by now.
They should not be stoned in that by you.
That was a thing.
I mean, there was a lot of prophecy going on that that, yeah.
Yeah, so we're not advocating for stoning anyone in that, right?
But if you follow the show, if you've read religiously apostles, right, you know that the
the language that's used in the Old Testament being cut off from among the people of the
that metal knee is applied in the New Testament.
It's not thrown away.
It's applied in the New Testament in the form of excommunication.
Right?
Because the life of Christ is the life of God.
That's real life.
Biological life is an image of that,
a derivative form of that.
That's the real life.
So being cut off from that is actually a worse punishment
a big son of a.
Yeah. Right. And again, reiterating the purpose of excommunication in the New Testament is
to drive someone to repent. Right. Exactly. Right. So the idea here is what we would be saying
is, if someone is under the spiritual delusion that they are a prophet, and it becomes clear
that what they're saying and claiming is from God is not from God, right?
Then they need...
to be cut off from youth people to God until they come to repentance, right, and come back
to the truth and back to Christ. Right. And the normal way that happens is excommunication,
which we see that in the New Testament. You know, someone, as it says, I mean, there's a very
strong language being handed over to Satan, you know, so that they would repent so that their soul
can be saved. Right. For the destruction of their body and the salvation of their soul. Right.
that the structure of the body is included.
is there to make the connection to the death battle these will be all tests of
unclear.
Yeah.
Does it?
So that's the idea, but the purpose is repentance. The purpose is to break that
delusion, right?
That someone is suffering under, because it's destructive to them as much as
everybody else, right? Because after the first few times you make those
prophecies and they turn out to be bogus people stop listening to you.
Sure.
That delusion can still do a lot of harm to you.
Yeah.
Even though everybody else is...
over it. So that's why it needs to be broken in that way. So but again we see in the Old Testament,
here at the end of our second half, we see that another point of continuity is that the
prophet in the Old Testament, because of this direct encounter with God and his direct relationship,
There are authority to rise from
that direct relationship. And so they stand this sort of an outsider over against the king
and the high priest and the priesthood in Israel. Right. Right. Right. That over against is
an opposed always. Sometimes. Right. It's better not let the king and the priest are doing.
But but they are sort of separate. They're sort of outside that. Yeah. That system. There's this
sort of right. It's not checks and balances exactly. But that's kind of the concept. You know,
in the
pen and authorities that, you know, and the prophet functions as this outsider.
Right. And so the prophet can then come to the king, you know, Nathan can come to
King David. Right. Right. And say, you know, those of us can come to Aaron and say,
you've done messed up a wrong.
It's straight about. Right. So there are, and so there are those structures,
but then there's also these prophets with whom God is dealing directly.
and who provide this important, right,
check this important, corrective.
And we see the Old Testament
with these prophets form communities, right?
We just use the example,
or talk about the example of Samuel
with this community of prophets around him.
We see this in the lives of Elijah and Elijah.
It talks about them going and staying on the other side
of the Jordan with the community of the prophets, right?
So there were these groups,
You know, these people were...
Mary, these people had children, right? But see, they're still kind of outside. They're in their own place. Right. Right. They're not within.
Right. And it's not just when it's corrupt. It's all the time.
Yeah. It's inherent to prophecy that it has this removal.
Right. This this removal. And so you even get some, not as extreme as we saw in the pagan world, but you get some kind of extreme forms of
Right, in the old testament and place.
We just talked about that whole episode with Saul. That's an example of an extreme episode.
You get with a Zekiel, for example. So a Zekiel is living with the other
deportees, right, in Babylon. And a regular Israelite community, but he does things like
wandering around naked for a while, right? Burning dumb and cooking over it, right? He does these
sort of bizzaro things right that separate him from everyone else right and
and that are a product of this direct experience with God.
So he is changed by it.
It's not in a physically destructive way.
Right.
But it isn't a way where they're sort of public displays
of being set apart and being different,
being outside, being having this different perspective.
Yeah.
On all things cultural.
Which is quite different from a lot of our modern glitzy
spectacular prophets who live at the top
of a very wealthy heap.
right? Generally speak. I mean, not all the time. But a lot of over that way. I mean,
that's they are not living in caves and exercising asceticism and...
Yeah. If Betty Hinn wanders the streets of, say, Omaha, bacon for seven years,
I will believe he is actually a pro. Wow. Previously, unsaid sentences and human history.
There you go. So that being said, we're going to go to our second and final break. We'll be
be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers in internet forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox Church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge. I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas. I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the...
Rick Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries,
and a priest of the Antioch in Archdiocese.
And where the Orthodox intro team is.
If you're looking for a first stop online to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends and not just toss them into the chaos of the internet,
a place to get help finding an orthodox period.
and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community.
Then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthroxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries
and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox on ramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's orthroxintro.org.
There it is. There's that metal version of our theme once more. Thank you Rob.
Well, I am your powers combined.
That's who are the Orthodox intro team.
Ah!
It's true. We're like Voltron.
Welcome back everybody.
It's the third half of our show on profits and prophecy.
In the first half, we talked about prophecy in paganism.
And the second half, we talked about prophecy
within Israel and the Old Testament.
And now we're talking about the New Testament.
I mean, are there still profits in the New Testament?
Isn't that just an Old Testament thing?
Wasn't John the Baptist the last?
The final, you know?
Yeah.
Is the church a non-profit organization?
Hey!
The answer is no.
We may think that.
And it is, we do refer to Old Testament states as prophets.
For example, and we do talk about
Saint John the four-honored being the culmination of the prophets.
Right.
Even sometimes the end of the prophets,
but uh...
Brief digression, word end, like tellos, and the words we usually translate as perfect in the New Testament in Greek.
Really be more mature or complete. Right. Right. The fullness of the prophets. And fullness. Yeah. Not like the last one.
and that's like perfect like flawless, right?
It means like, right?
So yeah, that's what we're saying.
about saying, John, right, is that he is the ultimate fullness. That doesn't mean, right?
Just like we said, Moses is sort of this paradigmatic prophet. That doesn't mean there weren't
any others, right? Right. So, um, and if anyone would want to say, well, no, I'm drawing
a heart and fast line. There are no prophets after saying John the four runner, you're going
to run into some problems when he gets the book of Acts.
Yeah, because that...
word is used very explicitly to refer to this one guy named Agabus.
Yes, Agabus. Also underutilized baptismal name.
Very true. I have never met an Agabus.
Yes, an Aggie is a perfectly good nickname.
If you're out there, Agabus.
If you're out there, Agabus, right in, tell us.
We want to hear from you.
Let us know
So Agamus, the prophet Agamus, he's explicitly identified as a prophet.
The two times he shows up in the Acts of the Apostles.
And the first time he shows up, he shows up in Acts 11 to warn everybody that there's
going to be a famine.
And he comes out of nowhere just in the classic prophetic style.
Right.
He's not like hanging around, he's not one of the...
He's not one of the seven deacons. He's not right. He's not in one of these sort of formal
Church leaders position position. He just shows up
And it has this mentioned and he's even announcing a famine. So I mean, this is like old school Elijah stuff, right?
This is say the liar stuff. He's doing
this classical prophet old desert prophet kind of thing as you can get
the second time he shows up he shows up at x21 and
And even
does this time he does some Ezekiel stuff right because Ezekiel was always called upon to do these sort of
visible things right take two stabs bind them together break them right this kind of thing yeah and
When Agabas shows up the second time in Acts 21 he shows up with his belt. Yeah, it's weird
He takes Paul's belt and and ties up his feet and hands right and says, you know
So I'll just read it thus says the Holy Spirit.
This is how the Jews had Jerusalem.
will bind the man who owns this belt and deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles. So he's prophesying Paul being
You know arrested right
Right, so he's doing this kind of weird prophetic act, right?
Which is very easy. So it's not just that the text calls of a prophet
It's not just he says that says notice thus says the Holy Spirit instead of thus says Yahweh
For all you people who don't who don't think the Holy Spirit being God is explicit in the New Testament
Um
Right.
It's not always the Holy Spirit, God, the Holy Spirit is Yahweh, according to this pattern.
It's not just that he's again doing something that the prophets in Scripture did, right,
doing this prophetic action, right, this display, right, which, you know, strictly speaking
isn't necessary.
Right.
You could have just showed up and said, it's been revealed to me by the Holy Spirit that,
You know, you're...
to get arrested. But everyone's going to remember how he took Paul's belt and
tied it around his pants and they're like, oh yeah. Right. Because this is part of this,
again, this prophetic thing, this sort of display. Right. So we have this profit in the book of acts.
Right. And the book of acts is not really like meditate upon his existence. No, he just comes and goes.
And it just takes your granted that yeah, there's a profit.
Agamus.
And so then we also find, especially in First Corinthians, St. Paul talking about prophecy.
And he's not talking about prophecy, like St. Peter talks about prophecy. He says no prophecy
was ever given by the world of men. He's talking about the Old Testament scriptures.
So St. Paul isn't talking about the prophets of old. He's talking about prophecy as a gift
within the Church of Jesus.
Corinth. So there are some prophets in the Church of Corinth or could be prophets in the Church of
Corinth. In 1 Corinthians 12 verse 10 he lists it as one of the gifts. Right. Right. That the spirit
has given to the church to some prophecy.
So this is parallel to the...
with these other kinds of gifts of teaching and these sort of things.
And when he brings it up in more detail in chapter 14 of 1 Corinthians, St. Paul is very deliberately
trying to distinguish the gift of prophecy from the gift of tongues.
Right.
I mean, it's pretty clear if you actually read the chapter, he doesn't say that they're
the same thing.
Right.
That can be easy.
He's literally arguing the exact opposite.
He's literally deliberately saying they're not the same thing,
which is a distinction that I think is lost on at least some of our
more charismatic friends, who tend to blend those things together a little more.
So the way he distinguishes this in particular is that he says
that tongues are directed toward the unfaith.
outside those outside the church. Right so it's an evangelistic tool. Right.
Whereas prophecy is directed toward those in the church toward the faithful.
Yeah a pastoral tool. Right. That makes them two different things. Right. And he says
clearly. And he says of course that tongues requires an interpreter and requires
somebody to explain what is being said which basically just means that he's
talking about what we saw.
in, you know, in acts at the day of Pentecost where they're speaking and people understand
in their own language.
You know, it's about foreign languages.
This is what we call Zeno Glossier, right?
That that's what he's talking about.
And the point of being able to speak foreign languages is so that you can preach the gospel
and evangelize.
Right.
So, this is, tongues is something directed outwards.
And so I don't know how you...
explain that from the current sort of charismatic view of tongue speaking.
Yeah, right.
Because that would seem to imply that tongue speaking of that kind,
Glossalelia, would be something you did toward unbelievers as an evangelistic tool.
Yeah.
And I don't think that's how it functions in those communities.
But that's how St. Paul says it's supposed to function.
Right, right.
And so that's why I think it's much more clearly the pentacost issue.
the ability.
speak other languages and say very basically don't say things in other languages if there's
nobody around who understands that language because it's pointless. Right. Right. It just
creates confusion. Right. Whereas prophecy again is toward the faithful. It's directed toward
toward the church. And so this is someone who has had this kind of direct encounter with God.
Yeah, right and
who is then going to share from that with the people of God.
And so we're going to argue a lot of the rest now of the third half is going to be making
the point.
It's a point I've made before, not as much detail on this show, but other places that
really are paradigmatic profit for the New Testament.
Right, if Moses is the...
magnetic profit in the Old Testament. The paradigmatic profit in the New Testament is actually St. Paul.
Okay, so how does that work?
And that's not how we're used to thinking of St. Paul.
Yeah, no, we don't call them the prophet Paul.
Yeah, because we've been trained by a long course of Western history. I'm looking at you,
St. Augustine and Martin Luther, to think about St. Paul in a very different way.
Right.
And...
And that starts with what gets called the conversion of St. Paul.
Right.
So both, and this comes from a fairly honest place with St. Augustine.
St. Augustine was himself a convert to Christianity.
After going through sort of a platonic phase and a mannequin phase and other phases,
comes due to Christianity. Right?
So he had this experience.
And so when he reads of St. Paul,
and when he reads St. Paul's letters,
he kind of over-identifies.
Yeah, right.
And since he over-identifies,
he kind of casts St. Paul as himself.
He says, this experience I had must be like the experience
St. Paul had when he converted from Judaism to Christianity.
Right.
Martin Luther of course is an Augustinian monk literally.
At an Augustinian influence also.
And he very quickly casts his own experience at a St. Paul's experience.
So the Pharisees of which St. Paul was one becomes medieval Roman Catholicism.
Alright, and St Paul becomes Martin Luther.
who has this change of religion, right?
That really it's all about faith, right?
No, that's all wet, right?
But neither of those is doing justice to St. Paul,
or the Pharisees, for that matter, right?
As they actually existed.
And neither of those is how St. Paul's experience is actually described.
Yeah, right.
And the first big clue to that is the fact that this happens in about AD 35
and there is
are not two separate religions.
Judy isn't in Christianity at the time.
Yeah, Christianity is a movement within the Judy and community.
Yes, and what that's only existed for a few years.
Right. Right. Like Christ's ascension was as long
as go is like Biden becoming president. Right.
Right. There's not been a lot of time for development here. Right.
So the idea that
say Paul was leaving one religion and joining another religion just does not work.
Yeah. Right. And just on the face of it. That's not what's happening. It can't be. Right.
So if we set that aside, if we start setting all this conversion stuff and the way we've
been taught to look at say Paul's eye and we look at how St. Paul describes it. Right.
Because not only does St. Luke describe it. Right. This episode on the road to Damascus gets
describes
several times in the New Testament. Yeah. It's a key event in the New Testament.
It gets derided, sort of as it happens in the narrative of Acts, it gets derided a second time
at the end of the book of Acts when St. Paul is speaking about it. And then it shows up again
in St. Paul's epistles. A couple of times he talks about it directly. Right? So we have a lot of
direct sort of testimony here from St. Paul.
and say, Luke, as do exactly what happened here and how it was understood by that.
So when he describes this experience, he's on the road to Damascus.
Christ appears to him. He sees Christ. He sees the Word of God, right? Word of God,
the Barrio, right? Christ the Word comes to him, speaks to him, reveals himself to him. He has
the strength encounter and then he sent.
On a mission.
Yeah.
And that word sent is pretty key because like the word apostle, a postalist in Greek means
one who is sent out.
And it's actually a, it's also a military term, right?
Like for a sortie as we would call it now, which is a good French word.
But it's a group sent out or a person sent out on a mission, right?
But that's not the first time that we see that word.
Right, not just in the New Testament that shows up in the Greek Old Testament, right?
Right. The verb, a post-alow that stands behind it, is the verb that's used, for example,
in the Greek of Isaiah. Here I am, send me. That's the verb for send.
Yeah. So it's already kind of a prophet, a word, a prophet, a prophetic.
the
Ingrig Isaiah is the one sent to use the Apostle of the divine council.
to Israel
So we see there this pattern, but but there's even more direct than that. So what are the places that St Paul talks about
This experience directly is in Galatians
That's about a fair amount of Galatians actually yeah, but and and
Every what
Right, everyone, every scholar who's actually a
scholar, accepts the St. Paul
Regulations. I know there's people who argue out of their
epistles. But I mean, friend of the show, Bart
Irman, I once saw it in a debate with the Jesus
Mythesis. And with the Jesus Mythesis, that he didn't
think St. Paul Regulations, Bart Irman laughed out loud.
They pretty much ended the debate. Because the guy didn't
like being laughed at. So even friend of the show,
Bart Irman knows that it's ridiculous to suggest that
say Paul did right regression. So this is
straight from Saint Paul. If anything is describing his experience, yes. Right. Okay. So this
is Galatians chapter 1 verses 11 through 16. For I would have you know, brothers, that
the gospel that was preached by me is not man's gospel. For I did not receive it from any man
nor was I taught it, but I received it through the revealing of Jesus Christ. For you have
heard of my former life in Judaism, how I persecuted the Church of God violently and tried
to destroy it. And I was advancing in
and beyond many of my own age among my people, so extremely zealous was I for the traditions of my fathers.
But when he who had set me apart before I was born and who called me by his grace
was pleased to reveal his son to me in order that I might preach him among the nations.
And that of course
parallels almost
almost identically in some ways the Greek quotes it.
Oh, the Greek actually literally quotes it.
There you go.
The Greek, you could throw in quotation marks.
Oh, interesting.
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, now this is not from the Greek,
but you'll hear basically that this is the same.
It's Jeremiah, chapter 1, verses 4 through 5.
Jeremiah speaking of himself.
Now the word of the Lord came to me and said,
before I formed you in the womb I knew you,
and before you were born, I consecrated you,
I have pointed you a prophet to the nations.
And...
And as you said, the Greek Old Testament, this is literally Paul is quoting that when
it's describing himself.
Right.
He's taking the same words and applying them to himself in terms of what happened again
on the road to Damascus.
Right.
So St. Paul saw what happened to him as a prophetic call like Isaiah had or like Jeremiah had
or like Moses's direct encounters.
Right?
he understood what had happened. And what else do we see in terms of parallels then? Well,
Moses has this direct encounter and he's sent with something, the Torah. In the same way,
let's say Paul is saying here in Galatians, he's sent with the gospel.
Moses receives the Torah during that encounter. St. Paul here in Galatians is saying he received
with Oswald in that encounter.
He didn't hear it from anybody else, he didn't get it from anybody else.
He received it from Christ in the way that Moses received the Torah from Christ on outside
eye.
Right.
And we even see, notice what happens to St. Paul after this encounter, note his way of life.
It becomes nomadic.
He travels from place to place.
And he's celibate unlike most of the apostles.
Yeah.
He's an outsider.
Right.
outside of
to the other apostles. Right. He functions as a corrector even to St. Peter. Right. And
he, you know, he says he makes this clear. Right. I didn't go after that experience. I didn't
go consult with the apostles in Jerusalem. I went out into the desert of Arabia. Yeah. Right.
He goes out into the desert by himself. He sort of thrust out into the desert by this experience.
Right.
And that's where he holds it.
And that's the same array.
where later in the same epistle he talks about outside I'd be in a right.
Which he's not identifying where I'm outside.
No, it's that I had a sign I experienced when I was in Arabia is essentially
right. Yeah. Right. And then you notice how he functions going forward even
with the other apostles, right? Coming to St. Peter and Antioch and calling him
to account. Yeah. I would stride away the process did with the priests and the
The Kings.
Right, or coming with a message to St. James and Jerusalem. Yeah, right where he's not part of those structures
Right and he's but he's functioning outside of those structures as an apostle to the nations because of this direct encounter
He's so St Paul is a prophet in the New Testament
Hmm
Hey, he's doing all the same things that the prophets do yes
This is not a different phenomenon.
is the same phenomenon.
And so we need to have a note here,
because of some previous episodes of things,
and some potential misunderstandings
that are what we're saying here, on visions.
Okay, so what's the...
And it's been dreams.
Yeah, I mean, I think most of the time
when people think of visions,
if someone said I had a vision,
they think, okay, you're deluded, dude,
you're seeing things.
Yeah.
hallucination. right exactly. yeah right. something not real. a mirage. right yeah yeah. that's not
what a vision is in scripture right or even a dream for that matter right when we think of dreams
we think of dreams is just being like well you're sort of brain computer is still churning while
you're asleep and it's processing the things from the day right or maybe you're a little more
sophisticated and in the cycle.
analysis, right? Then like your brain is representing things from your unconscious to you,
right? That you can't deal with while you're awake or whatever, right? But it's still
this sort of internal churning, right? Yeah. And not real. There's no, no sort of reality
too. So visions, right? In a scripture, when someone went, when Isaiah, right, has his vision
of Yahweh, he's not saying, I saw a hallucinatory icon of Yahweh, the God of Israel.
No, right. He's saying that God appeared to him. That God appeared to him. Not I had, I had,
I imagined, you know, it. Yeah. Jacob and Bethel. Yahweh standing on top of the Ziggurat.
Right. And a vision doesn't necessarily have to be like, like some, you know,
wavy, misty, whatever, because I mean, most of the visions that we get in scripture, it says,
is a young man
sitting at the right side of the tomb or something like that.
That's the way that visions usually work,
is there's nothing sort of,
woo, about them, you know?
Well, yeah, and what do they say?
They come back and they say,
we've seen a vision of angels.
The words say that angels weren't really there.
Right, right.
So vision is here functioning.
Gotta go back to our episode about the news.
Right?
the news, this perceptive faculty for the spiritual world,
is most commonly of our senses.
It is most commonly analogized to the eyes,
to see it more than to hearing or smelling.
Right, they're taking.
Right, right.
So that's the analogy that's made.
Right. And so, you know, when...
and Gahazi has his eyes opened by a lice and sees the hosts of the Lord, the angelic hosts.
Again, they're actually there.
He just did not perceive them before, but now he is.
So a vision is noetic perception, which most of us who are prophets don't do all the
time.
even most profits don't see.
to do all the time. Some of them seem to do it all the time. Some of them just some of
times. This isn't fake. This isn't something not real. This isn't the opposite of physical.
When St. Paul saw Christ, he saw Christ bodily. Christ's body, he saw Christ.
Cuz I'm gonna cry
still has a body. He is really there. When we say Christ is in our midst, we mean it.
Even though most of us don't see him, there are medications in this room of church where
someone has actually seen him. And they're really seeing him because he's really there,
we just don't perceive him directly. Because of the clotting of our news, because of saying,
et cetera, et cetera. See that episode. But this is also true of dreams. But because otherwise,
What are you gonna do?
when scripture tells us that St. Joseph the Betroth had an angel come to him in a dream.
Yeah, it doesn't say he dreamed up an angel. Right. He hallucinated an angel who told him something
and he believed it. It says an angel came to him and the place where the angel came and appeared to
him was in his dream while he was asleep. Yeah. And I think the fact that most of us don't have that
experience makes us analogize from our experience to that.
Right, I don't remember most of my dreams. I know people that remember all their dreams
You know, but I don't remember most my dreams and even the ones that I do I are a little hazy
You know, and I think that you know when someone says oh he had a dream that that's what they think that it must have been just like that
Right a little hazy like well, I don't know, you know, what does that mean whatever whatever
Little undigested bit of beef spot of mustard right?
Right, but there's a Dickens reference for the night
We need to consider that
If the mind is the news and not a churning away computer, then dreams also involve the
news, not a churning computer.
And so this is why, for example, in the Complin prayers, we pray, which are the prayers before
going to sleep, we pray that, during the night, God would dispel all the dark fantasies of
Satan.
like that, it's gonna come to the room.
places, dreams and things in dreams can come from places.
And enter in and are perceived by us in dreams.
So I don't think anyone would say, even though the scientific materialism kicks in and we want to say dreams are fake,
I don't think if someone came to us and said they had a horribly disturbing, like, sexually violent dream,
We would say
They're like, oh, it's just a dream, it doesn't mean anything to worry about, right?
Yeah.
We would take that seriously, right?
We would say, okay, something's going on here, right?
Because we know deep down dreams aren't actually fake, right?
There is something going on there, right?
Not all dreams are prophetic visions, but dreams are the activity of the news while you're
asleep.
Right, whereas what we call thoughts are the
activity of the news while we're awake.
Yeah.
It's just while we're awake, they're
joined by the five senses in a way that they're not usually
when we're asleep.
Yeah.
And it's interesting, you know, the question that we usually
ask of these experiences is, was that real?
Right?
Whereas, which I understand, like, why we feel like we need to go
there, but the question that's asked within Christian tradition
in scriptures not was that real but rather
where to come from.
And perhaps even more importantly,
what are you gonna do with it?
Yeah.
What does it mean?
Yeah, are you gonna repent?
Yeah.
Yep.
So yeah, so now all that's said, right?
So prophecy is firmly at the center
of the New Testament as a phenomenon.
So then people look at us, well, where is it
in the church today, then?
Yeah.
Right?
And what we're going to say is that primarily, not entirely, because just like in the Old Testament,
King David was a prophet.
Part of the whole prophet thing and the direct encounter with God thing is that God can
tunes to reveal himself to who member he wants.
So but generally, this is...
is a function of the monastic tradition in the church.
Yeah, I mean, you look at the way that they live.
They live these separate lives.
And the ones that are kind of the most associated
with all of these behaviors tend to live pretty separately.
They're even separate from them, right?
Like, if you go to Manothos, for instance,
most of the monks are living in the monasteries.
But there are these guys who live out by themselves
and caves.
and there's
even this tradition of the naked aesthetics who suddenly appear when they're needed and
then disappear when they're not.
There's all kinds of weird stuff that's right along these same patterns that we've been
talking about throughout this whole episode.
Right.
And so, monastic communities are this sort of direct continuation of the prophetic communities
of the old government.
What is it that is given as this great gift to the people who we would say?
have the gift of prophecy in this sense is the vision of Christ is uncreated glory.
Yeah.
Right. And that is not a different experience than the one that St. Paul had.
Right. It's literally the experience he had.
Literally the exact experience he had.
Right. And so, and we see how that that functions, right.
That throughout the history of the church,
the monastics have stood,
especially the
the, the, the, that's just how the gift of prophecy that sort of stood outside of, you know,
the established, right, the emperor, right, the patriarch, right, those hierarchies, they
stand outside of it at various points in the history of the church have come and challenged
the emperor. Yeah. Have come and challenged a bishop or two, right? Yeah. About their behavior
or about what they're teaching or about how they're exercising their offer.
And so in the same way that the prophet functioned over against the priest and king, we see that
happening in
this or the church and the saint who sort of articulated this
Like put it into so many words is really seems to me in the New Theologian
Right who literally talks about this kind of charismatic. Random charismatic is gift right?
Yeah, that's not this guy has a lot of charisma
about so you know people follow him right now.
This is the gift, right? They got the prophetic gift. He talks about the vision of Christ. He talks about this experience and he talks about how those who God is gifted with that kind of direct authority through this prophetic gift, then have the ability to speak against the established authorities when they become corrupt or when they become.
And it's important that that doesn't
We also have extreme examples within monasticism.
People who have this experience of God and have a more extreme reaction in how they then stand outside of society.
That's the holy fools. They're kind of, again, touched.
They behave in these insane ways.
seeing ways but it's insanity that leads to repentance for people that's right.
And it is undistructive to them or anyone else.
Right, it's a weirdness that's even
the sort of inherent weirdness of monasticism.
And what's interesting, it's interesting to me
that particularly the Russian tradition
really has a lot of these holy fools.
And I think that they seem to kind of multiply
as the empire gets bigger and more powerful.
Right, because you need more of that kind of thing
as worldly power accum-
And when you have, say, Cyril naked confronting Ivan the Terrible, that's not really very
different than his eat you'll go around naked.
Yeah.
Right.
And calling for the repentance of the people.
The fact it's the same.
But so there are these sort of extreme things or, or, pillar saints, right?
That means that our ideas are going to live on a pillar, right?
They've had this experience of that now sort of sets them apart.
But we always see the
part two, right? St. Seraphim of Surah goes out into the wilderness by himself, has this experience
of the vision of Christ and uncreating glory and ultimately he ends up opening up his cell so
that people can come and receive, right? The wisdom that he's received from God. Yeah.
So then you can pass it on. It's not just, oh God makes some people weird nose, right? Yeah. He
He has this relationship to the people of God,
and that's his purpose is to be this kind of...
anchoring tension. Right. Right. It's to be a prophet. Right. And speak to them the message that God
has for them. Yeah. And I, I mean, I think that one of the things that is really important to point
out about all this is that as you look at the history of prophecy in the people of God,
while they call these structures of power, especially to account, they don't subvert them.
It's about...
calling people to repentance, not about destroying the community or even destroying authority.
And the thing is that you can sometimes see, I think that there's a certain
millennianism that's crept into all of Western Christianity, including Orthodox Christians
that live in the West.
And maybe it exists elsewhere too, but this is the culture that I'm living in, that
You know, as I'm an American, so I participate in American.
culture, Americans have a streak within our culture of let's tear it all down and start over.
Like we just kind of love that idea. You know, this is not healthy people. It's actually not.
And sometimes we can interpret this tradition of ascetical charisma and the prophetic gift of
correction in those terms. You know, like like everyone disobey your priests and bishops and,
you know,
just listen to this one holy elder over here.
Whereas, I mean, whatever he's saying,
if he's functioning in the traditional role of profit
then what he's doing is actually calling everybody
a repentance and not saying everyone
leave your church communities.
You know, he's not destroying the community.
He's actually trying to heal it, right?
And I think that's a really important point.
He's not trying to destroy the community.
Like a true profit doesn't do that.
There are some, there are some revolutionaries out there
who are okay with it.
tearing everything down. Right so look at how the prophets function for example at the
Davidic monarchy. Right the Davidic monarchy produced the Messiah. That's the whole concept of
the Davidic monarchy. Yeah. That's leading to the Messiah, it's leading to Christ. Okay. So the
institution of the Davidic monarchy was a holy thing. Yeah. Right. That produced the Messiah. Right.
But the men who held the kingship in Judah were most often very wicked.
people. Yeah, right. There's very few that actually come off well in the Bible. God sends
prophet after prophet to the kings of Judea and to the people, the people of Judah to call
them to repentance as a gift to them. Right? Because he loves them and because of the importance of
the institution. Right. Right. To call them to repentance, never to undermine the institution.
right there's never called the like man people are too evil to have this
much power we need to get rid of monarchy or bishops or the priest. Right it was
never let's abolish the high priesthood let's forget this old tabernacle temple
thing. Yeah and you know I mean one of those reasons why that's important is
because profits aren't infallible either as we saw with Baalum extremely
fallible right they're not infallible either so you can't say well this is
And where all the authority is now and ignore everything else.
Right, so the prophetic institution, if we want to call it that, is there as part of God's
provision to make the institutions of priest and king function properly.
They need it to function properly.
It's actually a support for it.
If it weren't there, they'd collapse into tyranny and into false religion.
Right? If God hadn't sent a pro.
to Israel. All you would have had was the golden calves of Jeroboam, son of Nebath, and a bunch of
Wichon kings. Yep. Yep. Right? So the problem and so in the same way, right? It's a gift. And, you know,
if you really wanted an example of that, I know we're a few weeks past it now, but you can still go back and
read the life of St. Mary of Egypt and look at the way that St. Mary, who's a prophetic figure of ever there was one. Right?
Right, living in the desert, naked, free.
years. No food. Look at the way she reacts with Elder Zosuys who's a priest. Yeah. And I mean,
and that the and one of the last things that she says to him is, now look, I need you to go back
to the monastery because there's there's some problems and I need you to put them in order
and here's what the problems are. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, she she functions in this in this
corrective way. Yeah. Yeah. But but and she could
completely defer's though to the office, the institution of the priesthood.
Oh, yeah. Right. Right. Defer's to it does not speak a negative word against it.
Right. Right. Against that institution. So it's not about you should be that
monastery. You should be out here with me. Right. Yeah. It's, but she's functioning
how she's trying to restore health to that monastery. Yeah, exactly. Right. That's part of that.
that prophetic role.
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, I'm thinking...
of some of our final thoughts about prophets and prophecy and scriptures and elsewhere.
You know, I, you know, we've just talked about this question of how does the prophet function
relation to the rest of the community and the way that in my mind that works out is he's
not a revolutionary, he's a renewer, right?
That's his, that's his role as he wants to renew the community.
He wants to renew the church, he wants to renew society, that's his job and he does that
by standing outside of it.
and by having these encounters with Christ suffices to say this is not the life for everybody.
This is and it's not even a life for you know most of monasticism even though
monasticism as a whole institution functions in this prophetic way right but
but there's certain individuals that really do have this gift and I think one of
the ways that you can recognize that the prophet is a renewer and not a
revolutionary is that what he or she
Because there's some female seal,
we just mentioned St. Mary of Egypt.
What he or she has to say is actually not anything new
with regards to the revelation from God.
It's really about calling people back,
helping them to remember and to obey, again, the Lord, right?
And that's the task.
And I think that the way that modern people tend to think
about prophecy and the prophetic role is really not
That it might be there right? I'm not saying that everybody doesn't think of that or whatever
But often what we want is a kind of special revelation
Right, I need to have a special secret word, right? It's becomes this kind of we're back to divination right we're back to the
Pagan style of prophecy
I need some esoteric knowledge that I can't get in get in some other way
whether it's you know
the Bible code kind of stuff or or
you know what is God's will for my life in particular should I do?
this or that, so I turned left to right. But I think that the cure for a lot of that kind of thinking
is found in the parable that Christ tells of the rich men in Lazarus, right? Where they both die,
Lazarus is in Abraham's bosom with Abraham, and the rich man is entormate. And the rich man
and says, you know, Abraham sends Lazarus back from the day.
to go help my brothers and Abraham says to him, look, they have Moses in the
prophets. You know, let them hear them and you know, the rich man says no, no, you
know, if someone came back from the dead, then they'd believe and Abraham says,
well, if they're not going to believe Moses in the prophets, they wouldn't
believe even if someone did come back from the dead. Which of course, you know, this
is speaking about Christ's resurrection on certain level. But also, when Abraham
makes this appeal to Moses and the prophets.
That's to say in this particular context, look, they don't need some special revelation.
They just need to become obedient to the revelation that we've all been given.
Again, much of the scripture is considered to be prophetic books within the scope of
the scripture, meaning that it is given by God as a story told by God about who we are,
We are now who we've been where we are now where we're going and most especially
where what we need to be obedient to. And I think that that's this notion of Moses and the prophets.
We've been given that. We've been given the scriptures. We've been given the tradition of the church.
If I want something other than that, I think that's, I have a big problem.
Right? I have a humility problem. I, you know, I don't know. There's all kinds of ways that
that's a problem.
And, you know, one of my
my face.
writers because he's so witty as GK Chesterton who I don't know I've never checked
now that I think about it as whether he said this or not for sure but a saying
attributed to GK Chesterton maybe he did say it was Christianity has not been
tried and found wanting it has been found difficult and not tried and I I
believe that one of the difficulties that we have as modern Christians is that
that.
In many cases, we haven't really tried it.
Or we've tried bits, you know, if I'm speaking of myself, I've tried some of Christianity,
but there's still a lot that I have not been obedient to.
And I don't know, it doesn't make sense to want special revelation if I haven't actually
acted on the revelation that I have.
So when we think about prophecy, that I think is our starting point.
that all of these profits
that we already have that we should receive them in the way that God sent them to call us
to repentance, to bring us back to faithfulness and obedience to the Lord.
And that's a compelling call.
That is a compelling call.
So all right, Father Stephen.
So it's really easy for us to sound.
like a couple of orthodox priests here. Sound like we're picking on our charismatic friends
when we talk about folks who claim to be prophets and then say whatever political statement,
whatever thing they hope happens, but this is a prophecy from God and the point of them is false
profits and maybe you would seem like we're laughing at them.
But I think, and I'm sure this is not
And back I know this isn't exclusive to orthodoxy, but since orthodoxy we should probably talk about our orthodoxy brethren first and foremost.
We've got a lot of false prophets of our own. And it's false prophets in a little bit of a different sense.
in that we've been very much acculturated in the United States to kind of want to see
ourselves as a take on.
the role that profits play over against
institutions and the establishment
without necessarily being called to take it, right?
So you watch Star Wars, the Rebels are the good guys.
We don't make TV shows and movies about an honest cop who follows all the rules
Right, we make TV shows and movies about the tough cop and plays by his own set of rules.
We don't want to
be like a lieutenant in the Gotham City Police Department. We want to be Batman working outside the system,
to bring justice, right? That's sort of our whole ethos, right? I'm the one who's going to stand up
and point out to all these bishops why they're wrong and they're all cell-ups. I'm the one who's
going to fix the church and straighten everything out, right? I'm the new St. Maxime, the confessor,
right because he was a lay person and I'm a lay person.
you could do this, right?
Or, you know, pick your priests
who had to oppose his vision behind that.
And what we're doing when we do that,
and I've even been guilty of that in the past.
I hope only the remote past,
but maybe there's elements of myself I don't see
and I'm still guilty of it.
Is we're being like those prophets in Jeremiah
who God didn't send, but we come running,
because we're eager to get at it.
We're eager to sort of be Saint Maximus the confessor in the sense that we're going to speak
our truth of power.
We're not so much eager to be Saint Maximus the confessor in getting our tongue cut out
and our hand cut off and actually suffering.
That not so much.
But we want to be the ones who are going to straighten everybody else out and speak this truth
these powerful people who were totally certain, they're totally corrupt unlike us.
And that's not what St. Paul means when he says we should seek the gift of prophecy.
That's the opposite, right?
This is what that whole parable Christ tells us about the splinter in the eye and the log
in the eyes about.
The way that one seeks the gift of prophecy is you seek the first part.
seek the experience of God.
You don't try to form your own mission.
You don't try to piece together your own message which you're going to claim as from God.
But you seek that first part, encounter with God, the experience of God.
And we know, or at least we should know if we're listening to the scriptures, if listening
to the church, how you do that.
You do that by repenting.
You do that by purifying yourself.
You do that by being faithful.
You do that by loving others.
emotionally or mentally but concrete.
showing love to others through acts of kindness and assistance and help and
self-sacrifice. If we pursue that and if we do that then it may be at the time
of God's choosing, in the way of God's choosing, to the extent of God's
choosing, He may reveal Himself to us. And when He reveals Himself to us in
whatever way do whatever extent.
He may then have some task for us that we need to do.
And it may be that, including in that task, it might be correcting someone.
But to jump to that is putting the cart before the horse.
It's saying that Christ said something that He didn't say.
It's saying that He sent us when He didn't send us, we just came running.
It's putting the...
cart before the horse. And so we should, as St. Paul says, pursue the gift of prophecy.
We should seek to come to know Christ ever more deeply to experience him directly. We have
the opportunity more than once a week in a lot of cases, but at least once a week, most
of us have the opportunity to receive Christ himself into our bodies and then be sent
out.
We have the
opportunities we know what we need to do, right? But doing it requires this long
hard work and doing it may require a lot of suffering, may require persecution,
may even require margarineau, right? We may end up becoming like St. Maximes and
all the ways that we don't want to become like him in our flesh rather than
in the ways we think we want to become like him because of our pride and
and our vanity. But that's what the person...
of the gift of prophecy looks like.
It's never something we can demand from God.
It's never something that there's a technique
that will guarantee it.
But it is a possibility that is out there
if we're diligent about living the Christian life.
And if we do that, if we purify ourselves,
if we repent, if we're loving,
we may never receive the gift of prophecy.
We may never receive the vision of Christ in uncreated glory.
That may not be what God has.
for us. We may never be sent to correct everyone and save the church, but we just might find
salvation for ourselves, for our own souls, for our own lives. And that is what we're really
after in the end, not the other.
Amen. Well, that is our show for today. Thank you very much for listening, everyone. If
you didn't get to listen to us live, we'd still love to hear from you. You can email us
at Lord of Spirits and Ancient Faith.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share the show with a friend whom you know is going to love it, or even someone who's kind of okay into it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, Struct Support.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
And while you're there, order Father Jeremy's book on
Sacrifice.
Hey, good idea.
Thank you very much.
Good night, everyone.
God bless you.
Christ has risen.
He truly is risen.
You've been listening to the
of spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
wisdom and strength and honor.
and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.